<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon the government of the Kingdom of France during the reigns of Henry the Fourth, sirnamed the Great, Lewis the Thirteenth, sirnamed the Just : but more at large of Lewis the Fourteenth, sirnamed Given of God, the Great, and the Invincible.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53179</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11769068</idno>
  <idno type="VID">48812</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240891122</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O118A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31045</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11769068</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1490:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon the government of the Kingdom of France during the reigns of Henry the Fourth, sirnamed the Great, Lewis the Thirteenth, sirnamed the Just : but more at large of Lewis the Fourteenth, sirnamed Given of God, the Great, and the Invincible.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 116 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Observations upon the government of France, etc.</note>
                  <note>Frontispiece portrait of Louis XIV of France.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  Politics and government --  1589-1789.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:48812:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of a man</figDesc>
                  <head>REX GALLIAE LVDOVICVS XIV</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48812:1"/>
            <p>Observations upon the GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF FRANCE, DURING The Reigns of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, Sirnamed the <hi>Great,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, Sirnamed the <hi>Just,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But more at large of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, Sirnamed, <hi>Given of God,</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> and the <hi>Invincible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48812:2"/>
            <head>To his GRACE the DUKE of ******</head>
            <opener>May it please your Grace,</opener>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I</hi> Once thought this Trifle capable of affording me Diversion, yet, though I much desire it, I cannot think it Worthy of meriting your Grace's Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. The Piece it self in many places being of no Value, and the Performance in the Translation is so every where, which is the reason I prefix neither your Grace's Name nor my Own. The thing I am most proud of in the World, is your Graces Favour and Acquaintance; and is what I will ever glory in upon all other occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet, resolving, never publickly to own my self a Scribler. It is not just your Name, for which I have so much Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, should be placed before that, which I fear may bring my own Sence into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion:
<pb facs="tcp:48812:3"/>However, there is this advantage in being Concealed, that your Grace can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be censured for your Friendship, to a Person Ʋnworthy of so much Goodness. I wish I were able to give your Grace a more particular Account of this Tract; but I could never learn any thing of it, but that it came from <hi>Holland.</hi> It was shown me many Months since, and then Translated. It is a Collection made up of Panegyrick and Scandal; and if in some places it is more favourable than the base Character deserves, the Collector is not to blame, who doubtless was a French Man; and, though he be severe enough upon his Princes, is yet much a <hi>Boutan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> whose Servile and Ʋncleanly way of Honouring their <hi>Grand Monarque</hi> (described by Mons. <hi>Tavernier</hi>) deserves to be Proverbially applied, not only to many of the French, but their Slavish Mimicks.</p>
            <p>I guessed this would not be Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, if made English, to shew what blessed People those were, whose Conduct and Government, not long was so much admired by some of their Neighbours. The
<pb facs="tcp:48812:3"/>Vertues of those Pillars of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> here mentioned, was yet a greater Inducement, and made me huddle it over the quicker (to which, I hope, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>correctness will be ascribed) that it might get into the World, when their Impudence and Tyrany was most Rampant here. That it has lain thus long, I matter not, let him look to that, who is to get by it (if he can.) The Observations on Mons. <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne,</hi> I imagine, by the Style in French, to be done by a different Hand; the few things mentioned here, are otherwise re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated then in his Printed Life: And I doubt not but your Grace, whose delight is Arms, Honor, and the good of your Country, will be pleased enough with the matter, and pass over the defects of Expression. As to the Reasons of Mar. <hi>Turenne</hi>'s shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apostacy, I differ from the Author; for whether he were Cheated into it, like many others, by the Bishop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s New Popery, or led by some other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, very unlike the rest of the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of his Soul and Ʋnderstanding. I know not, but cannot help thinking, it is the most villanous Blot in his, or any
<pb facs="tcp:48812:4"/>other reasonable Mans Life; and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of an Apology, as the Heresie he embraced, is of an honest Defence: Thus, Sir, whilst I am incognito, I have taken the liberty of an Impertinent Masquera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and talked more than comes to the share of a Dedicator; but since I am no needy Mercenary one, I think my self the less bound up to their Methods: Yet were I not sensible that your Grace has with your Wit and Judgment, a wonderful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desention and Obligingness, I should not have thus presumed; but your Grace finds that it is the Fate of those, who are universally Admired and Beloved, to be as often Importuned, as Pleased; and if I have trespassed on good Breeding, I beseech your Grace, to believe it to be the Zealous effect of both my Inclination and Choice, ever to Honour you, and be with respect,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Grace's most Obedient and most Humble Servant,</hi> †††††††.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48812:4"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS Upon the GOVERNMENT OF THE Kingdom of <hi>FRANCE,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. I. <hi>Concerning the Sirname of</hi> Great, <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to</hi> Hen. <hi>the Fourth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>French</hi> Writers have usually compared <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> to the Conqueror of <hi>Asia:</hi> For <hi>Alexander</hi> was of a low stature, but of an invincible Courage; and a <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> Embassador very handsomly insinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it in an Eloquent Discourse, to these excellent Expressions, <hi>Si magnitudinem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48812:5"/>tui corpus tuum aequaret, universus Orbis non te caperet, altera manu contingeres Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem, altera Occidentem.</hi> If thy Body were equal to thy Courage, the whole World wou'd not contain thee; for with one Hand thou wou'dst touch the <hi>East,</hi> with the other the <hi>West. Juvenal</hi> speaking of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and alluding to his being a little Man, says,
<q>
                     <l>Unus Pellaeo Juveni non sufficit Orbis.</l>
                     <l>— Mors sola fatetur</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quantula sint hominum Corpuscula.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Our Illustrious <hi>Henry</hi> was a little short Man, but his small Body contained a Noble Heroical Soul; and in his time the <hi>French</hi> applied that Proverb to him,
<note n="*" place="margin">Petite mine &amp; grand jeu.</note>
                  <hi>Small appearance and Great matters.</hi> He had the Title of Great for his valiant Actions; which made him be look'd upon as the Balancer of the World. And for his intirely suppressing the League, and driving Foreign Enemies out of the very Heart of his Kingdom; these Verses were therefore usually put under his Picture, or Statue:
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Endomtant mes sujets, guerroyant l'Etranger,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>La gloire de mon Nom n'a pont eu de seconde.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48812:5"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Et lors que le destin vint mes jours abreger,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Je m'etois fait Monarque &amp; l'Arbitre du Monde.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By Taming Rebels, Conquering Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Foes,</l>
                        <l>The Glory of my Name no equal knows.</l>
                        <l>But when I fell by an untimely Fate,</l>
                        <l>I was the Balance of all <hi>Europe's</hi> State.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This Gallant Prince was so overjoy'd, when he was compared to <hi>Alexander,</hi> that he gave a very great reward to <hi>Malherbe</hi> the Poet, for four Verses he made <hi>extempore</hi> upon a little Horse that this Monarch rid upon.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Petit Cheval, gentil Cheval,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Propre à montrer, propre à descendre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu n'és pas tant que</hi> Bucéphal.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu portes plus grand qu'</hi> Alexandre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pretty Horse, little Horse,</l>
                     <l>Yet fit to bear the World's Commander.</l>
                     <l>Thou want'st <hi>Bucephalus</hi> his Force,</l>
                     <l>Thy Lord surpasses <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Some are apt to think that the Sirname of <hi>Great,</hi> was not given to this King for his great Actions only, but for the design he had of giving <hi>France</hi> the bounds it had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48812:6"/>of Old, so that he intended to extend the Kingdom <hi>Eastward</hi> to the <hi>Rhine, West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> to the <hi>Pyrenean Hills, Southward</hi> to the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and <hi>Northward</hi> to the <hi>Ocean;</hi> but the untimely Death of this Monarch stop'd this great Work, which has still been endeavoured at by his Successors; and the present King seems to be pretty well advanced toward it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. II. <hi>Of the First Marriage of</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF ever any King was Unfortunate in his Marriages it was he; for, though his Heart were very sensible of Love, and his Inclinations to it too Violent; yet it was always his Fortune to find full as much Dissatisfaction, as Pleasure in his Amours. His First Marriage with <hi>Margaret</hi> of <hi>Valois,</hi> was only made for a blind, the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the specious Pretence of that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, to commit that Massacre on St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi>'s Day; in which, against all the Rules of Wisdom, they contrived the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of <hi>Henry,</hi> who was then but King of <hi>Navarre.</hi> There hapned then an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48812:6"/>accident very surprising, which was, that when the Massacrers sought him, to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatch him, he was sitting alone in a Room with his Wife; and seeing every Place streaming with the Blood of his best Friends, and these Villains hastning to cut his Throat, he thought of hiding himself after this manner; Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> sate in a great Chair, and at that time Farthin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales were worn, which made their Petty-coats stand out round, our <hi>Henry</hi> hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self underneath, between his Wives Thighs. The Assassinates having broke open the Door, and seeing no Body but the Queen, ask'd her where the King her Husband was? She without changing her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or shewing any Concern, haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told 'em he went away from her in a great deal of haste; so that these Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, who always look'd upon this Lady with a great deal of respect, departed without Executing their purpose; and, therefore it was merrily said, That <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets</hi> Petty-coats saved King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Life.</p>
               <p>This Queen was the Sister of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. of the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> afterwards King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> III. and of the Duke of <hi>Alenson.</hi> She had extream Violent Inclinations to two things, that were very different, Learning and Love; so that she
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48812:7"/>was called the <hi>Minerva</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> It is a Common report that she made good Verses, with great readiness; and it is a known Story, that this Princess one Day taking the Air, saw a Poor Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lying on a Dunghil, she said to him, <hi>Pauper ubique jacet;</hi> which he hearing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently writ down this Distich, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to her.
<q>
                     <l>In thalamis, Regina, tuis hac nocte jacerem;</l>
                     <l>Si verum hoc esset, pauper ubique jacet.</l>
                  </q> Whereupon as soon as this pleasant Lady had read them, she sent him these <hi>extempore,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Carceris in tenebris plorans hac nocte jaceres;</l>
                     <l>Si verum hoc esset, pauper ubique jacet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed this Princess was so fond of Learning, that she continually entertained at her Table the greatest Scholars of the Kingdom. As for what concerns her Love, it's said, that she never denied her Lovers any thing; and <hi>Henry,</hi> who let her do what she pleas'd, rather look'd upon her as the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Sister, than as his own Wife, for neither of them had that Love for each other, which is necessary for a real Marriage. But she was afterwards Divorced from <hi>Henry</hi> for her Barrenness; but after the Dissolution of the Marriage,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48812:7"/>the good Lady by a Lover of hers had two Children. She had been brought up, and incouraged in these Practices, by her own Mother <hi>Catharine de Medicis,</hi> who was usually called the fourth Fury of Hell, as appears by these Verses, said to be made by Q. <hi>Marg.</hi> her own Daughter.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tres Erebi Furias post hac, ne credite Vates,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Addita nam quarta est his Catharina tribus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod si tres furias de se dimiserit Orcus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haec Catharina tamen pro tribus una foret.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That there are but three Furies; think no more,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Catharine</hi> is added to make four.</l>
                  <l>Nay, were the rest from their dark Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion gone,</l>
                  <l>Their place might be supplied by her alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This Queen <hi>Catharine,</hi> as <hi>Thuanus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, was very Cunning, and of a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Temper; and had a Company of Fortune-tellers and Conjurers that always followed her, and because they had all Foretold her that she should be Destroy'd the Ruins of a House, <hi>qu'elle seroit accablée sous les Ruines d'une Maison;</hi> she never would go into any till her Work-man had Survey'd it, to know if it were strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Built. But after the Death of the Duke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48812:8"/>of <hi>Guise,</hi> and the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain</hi> his Brother, who were kill'd at <hi>Blois,</hi> and were the great Creatures and Favourites of this Queen; she took it so to Heart, that she fell Sick and Died of Grief. A little before she expired, she had two La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies near her, one of them was a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, and the other a Papist, who both Exhorting her to lift up her Soul to God her Maker, and implore his Divine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; she spoke these Words, <hi>My good Friends now my Days are ended by the Ruins of a House.</hi> For of all her Sons, there now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remained <hi>Henry</hi> III. who had no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor had hopes of any, so that the House of <hi>Valois</hi> was at an end.</p>
               <p>They say, that she made use of the Conjurations of these Wizards, to know who should succeed her Sons; which they did by the means of a Looking-glass, and shewed her who should have the Crown after the Race of <hi>Valois.</hi> The First that appeared was our <hi>Henry</hi> IV. for whom she had such an Aversion, and so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placably hated him, that ever after she used her uttermost endeavour to destroy him. <hi>Notúmque furens quid foemina possit,</hi> but God delivered him from all her snares. After him she saw in the Glass <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. and then appeared one with a stately Mien and Majestick Air, which was <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48812:8"/>After whom the Magick-glass shewed her a Company of Jesuits, who were to have their turn to be absolute Masters of <hi>France.</hi> She then wou'd see no more, and was ready to break the Glass; but, however it was preserved, and it's reported that it is kept at present in the <hi>Louvre.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. III. <hi>Concerning the Second Marriage of</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> was Unfortunate in his First Marriage, he had but very little better Fortune in his Second, except his Posterity. For the first Night he lay with his Wife <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> there was fix'd over his Bridal Chamber, in great Letters, these Words of the Scripture, <hi>Non erat opus Bene-valentibus Medicis;</hi> which was a Satyrical allusion to the Queens Family, who was Daughter to the Great Duke of <hi>Tuscany,</hi> of the House of <hi>Medicis.</hi> These Illustrious Lovers did not always agree very well, their particular Intrigues made 'em often Quarrel; the Queen had great Heart-burnings, to see the Kings several Mistresses; and the King could not bear
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48812:9"/>the Queens Leudness with the Marquis of <hi>Ancre</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> that was her Favorite. One Night, when they lay together, after some Curtain-lectures, and sharp Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of each other, the Queen got up, and flew at his Face, and in the heighth of her Auger scratch'd him soundly; the King for his part spared her no more than she did him; so that to end this Combat, those of the Bed-Chamber then in Wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were fain to run and call the Duke <hi>de Sully,</hi> Lord Treasurer, who had a great ascendant over the King's Temper, he hastned to the <hi>Louvre</hi> and after he had very much intreated the King, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated to him how scandalous it was; he obliged him, to hinder further disorder, to quit the Field, and carried him to lodge in another Chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. IV. <hi>Concerning the Temper, and Disposition of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> Great.</head>
               <p>THe Servants that were most intimate with this Prince, have always tax'd him with want of Gratitude, and not rewarding those that were most Faithful
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48812:9"/>and Loyal to him, which Monsieur <hi>d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigny</hi> very smartly expressed; for when the King had given him his Picture, as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Reward and Favour, he was so bold as to write these Verses under it.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ce Prince est d'etrange Nature,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Je ne sçai qui Diable l'a fait;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Car il récompense en Peinture</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ceux qui le servent en effet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This Prince is of a very odd Nature,</l>
                     <l>Who the Devil made him so?</l>
                     <l>Though he's substantially serv'd by his Creature,</l>
                     <l>He only rewards him with shadow and show.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>But yet we may see an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Instance of his Liberality in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent he made of his House at
<note n="*" place="margin">The Arrow.</note>
                  <hi>La Fleche</hi> to the Jesuits, which is the noblest College they have in <hi>France.</hi> Of this College and another call'd <hi>L'Arc,</hi> or the Bow, which they have at <hi>Dole,</hi> in <hi>Franche Comté,</hi> one who was no Friend to their Order, made this Distich,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Arcum</hi> Dola <hi>dedit Patribus, dedit Alma Sagittam</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Gallia; <hi>quis funem quem meruere dabit?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48812:10"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dole</hi> gave the Bow, <hi>France</hi> did the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row bring;</l>
                     <l>But who shall give what they deserve, the String?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Jesuits answer'd in French to this purpose,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>L'Arc &amp; la Fleche sont à nous</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Prêts à décocher contre vous,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mais pour ce qui est de la Corde</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Elle est à vous, je vous l'accorde.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Bow and the Arrow we have,</l>
                        <l>Which we are ready to shoot against you</l>
                        <l>To you the String we will leave,</l>
                        <l>Because we think it your due.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Which was answered.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>L'Arc &amp; la Fleche vous avez</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>De la</hi> France <hi>&amp; de</hi> l'Espagne;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mais pour la Corde vous l'aurées</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Du Roi de la</hi> Grande Bretagne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Arrow you from <hi>France</hi> did gain,</l>
                        <l>The Bow was given you by <hi>Spain:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But we hope from <hi>England</hi>'s King</l>
                        <l>You'll have what fits you best, the String.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But if <hi>Henry</hi> the Great did not bestow
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48812:10"/>his Rewards so liberally as his Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, who said, he only shared the whole Kingdom with his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Servants, yet he had another qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which, in some measure, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for his want of Liberality, which was, that he patiently endured his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants Complaints and Reproaches without being angry. And there is a remarkable Instance of it; for once when Monsieur <hi>La Force</hi> and <hi>D'Aubigny,</hi> two of his Favorites, lay together in a Field-bed, near his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Bed, Mr. <hi>D'Aubigny</hi> thinking the King had bin fast asleep, began as he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually did, to complain of the King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, very often repeating to <hi>La Force,</hi> who was just dropping asleep, and snor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sir, our Master is the basest and most ungrateful Fellow upon the face of the Earth; and as the other who was slumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, only replyed, What say'st thou, <hi>D'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigny?</hi> The King, who was awake, and heard this goodly Dialogue, cryed out, <hi>La Force,</hi> Hearken a little; dost thou not hear what <hi>D'Aubigny</hi> says? how that I am the basest and most ingrateful Fellow upon the face of the Earth: And yet, for all this, he never mentioned it to either of 'em ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. He was extreamly pleased with Raillery, and a thing well and home said; of which there are several Examples in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48812:11"/>but this I have not read, which is that in that time there was a severe Song made upon the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> called, <hi>La Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che à Colas,</hi> or <hi>Nick</hi>'s <hi>Cow,</hi> (or may be, like <hi>Colly my Cow;</hi>) which was burnt at <hi>Paris</hi> by the Hangman, and all people of what quality soever, were forbid singing it, but the Prohibition made it be sung the more. One day, when the King was in the <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre</hi> with some Courtiers about him, the Duke <hi>de la Force,</hi> then Captain of the Guards, came towards the King in great haste, the Count <hi>de Grammont,</hi> who was his mortal Enemy, was by, who, to abuse him, sung these Words aloud,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Voicy venir</hi> la Force,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qui vient à grand Force,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Voir la Vache à Cola,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fa, la, la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Here comes <hi>la Force</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With all his Force,</l>
                        <l>To see <hi>Nicklis</hi>'s Cow.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The King was pleased with this, and made it be repeated when <hi>La Force</hi> was come to them, who immediately addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himself to <hi>Grammont,</hi> who was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Cuckold by all the Court,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48812:11"/>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Les Cornes de la Vache</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Serviront de Panache</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A</hi> Grammont <hi>que Voila,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fa, la, la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Cows horn</l>
                        <l>For a Plume, may adorn</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Grammont,</hi> that stands there,</l>
                        <l>When he feathers will wear,</l>
                        <l>Fa, la, la, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The King, turning to <hi>Grammont,</hi> cry'd, <hi>Ventre St. Gris,</hi> Thou art paid home; and they say, that this disgusted <hi>Grammont,</hi> to that degree, that he immediately left the Court, and never appear'd there more. But to return to our <hi>Henry,</hi> his faithfullest Friends have thought his Love for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses was too violent; for it was to that degree, that to enjoy one of them, which is reported to be the fair <hi>Gabrielle d'Estrée,</hi> before he was married to <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> be took some of his own Blood to sign a Promise of Marriage; but Monsieur <hi>de Sully,</hi> Superintendent of the Finances, or Treasurer, seeing that Writing, tore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King's Face, the King saying, <hi>Ventre St. Gris,</hi> I believe you are mad; yes, Sir, replyed <hi>Sully,</hi> but wou'd to God I were the only Mad-man in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Another time Madam <hi>D'Entragues</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48812:12"/>made him promise to give her 50000 Crowns the first time he lay with her, and going out of this noble Mistress's Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and seeing Monsieur <hi>de Sully</hi> in the Antichamber, telling out the Sum, asked him, who that Mony was for? <hi>Sully</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering, it was for Madam <hi>d'Entragues,</hi> says the King, <hi>Ventre St. Gris,</hi> this is a damnable dear Nights Lodging. Indeed <hi>Demosthenes</hi> said of <hi>Thais</hi> the Courtizan, <hi>Tanti Paenitere non emo:</hi> They say he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted several mean things to come at his Mistresses, sometimes disguising himself like a Country Fellow, sometimes like a Porter or Labourer, to get at them with more ease.</p>
               <p>In point of Religion, he was justly counted by all <hi>Europe</hi> a mere Turn-coat: He was born a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick; but <hi>Jane,</hi> Queen of <hi>Navarre,</hi> his Mother, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly instilling into him the Principles of the Protestant Religion, he afterwards made open profession of it at <hi>Rochelle,</hi> and was there declared the Protector of the Protestant Churches in <hi>France.</hi> At the Massacre of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> to save his Life, he was forc'd to change again, but it was only in appearance; for two years after he fled from the Court, and being come to <hi>Alenson,</hi> he abjured the Papist Religion, and continued a Protestant till
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48812:12"/>he came to the Crown. He used to say, <hi>Ventre St. Gris,</hi> the Crown of <hi>France</hi> sure is worth a Mass; but as his Heart did not go along with his Mouth, when he saw others follow his Example, he used to tell them, Why do you change? you have no Crown to gain. However, some time after he quite changed his Mind, by the Jesuites Endeavours, that were about him, especially Father <hi>Cotton,</hi> whom he had great Confidence in. For a few days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Murther, going to <hi>Fountain-bleau,</hi> and the Regiment of Guards with him, it began to rain very hard, and therefore letting his Guards march before, he staid behind alone with Monsieur <hi>de la Force,</hi> who was a Protestant and his Favourite, and talking familiarly with him of the two Religions, he spoke these Words with a great air of Sincerity, My good Friend, the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion is not so full of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as I thought it was heretofore. Which plainly shews that he was no longer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, but firmly perswaded of the truth of that Religion.</p>
               <p>This Great Prince was so very sensible of the Malice of <hi>Catharine de Medicis,</hi> that he used to say to his Confidents, There are four things when I think of them, that fright me, <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Magick Glass, her Clock, her Bed, and St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi>'s
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48812:13"/>Massacre, which was contrived by her and her Son the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> after King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and then King of <hi>France,</hi> who, for his Device, used to give two Crowns, and a third pointed with Stars, with this Inscription, <hi>Manet ultima Coelo.</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the front of the <hi>Louvre, Triplicem dabit ille Corona.</hi> To which was satyrically added,
<q>Tertia sic dabitur, tenuit velut ante secundam.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The day that this potent Monarch was stab'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Street of the <hi>Feronnerie,</hi> there hapned a surprising thing in <hi>Bearn.</hi> As the Duke <hi>de la Force</hi>'s Son, who was Vice-Roy of <hi>Navarre,</hi> was walking with abundance of Gentlemen, by the little River of <hi>Pau,</hi> all the Cows that were in the Meadows, at the same time, ran with an extraordinary violence, so that it was impossible to stop them, and threw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves headlong into the <hi>Pau,</hi> and were drowned. This was lookt upon as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy; and the Vice-Roy observ'd the time and hour that it hapned, very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, as thinking it might presage some Disaster; and so it hapned, for a few days after there came an Express of that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Parricide committed upon the King's Person, at the very same hour the Cows drowned themselves. The reason of this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48812:13"/>is, the Cows are part of the Arms of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> where this hapned.</p>
               <p>But while this gallant Prince designed great things, and had raised a numerous Army, he was barbarously murther'd by <hi>Ravaillac,</hi> in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> and the Year 1610. which, in few words, hapned after this manner.</p>
               <p>He went from the <hi>Louvre</hi> to visit the Duke of <hi>Sully</hi> at the <hi>Arsenal,</hi> who was sick, and passing through a Street near St. <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi>'s Church-yard, which then was very narrow, called the <hi>Feronnerie;</hi> his Coach meeting with Hay-carts, was stop'd: And the Footmen that ran by the sides, were forced to quit it: At this moment the Monster <hi>Ravaillac</hi> got near the Coach, and setting his Foot upon one of the Wheels, struck the King (who sat at the end of the Coach, and then lean'd upon the Duke' <hi>d'Espernon</hi>) with a Knife, which leaning stretcht his Body, and made him lye so open, that it proved mortal. The King cryed, I am hurt, and then <hi>Ravail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac</hi> stab'd him again into the very Heart. He never spoke after the second stroke, but only fetcht a great Sigh, and groaned a little. So that this Verse of <hi>Virgil</hi> was very well applyed to him.</p>
               <q>Vita{que} cum gemitu fugit indignata sub umbras.</q>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48812:14"/>
               <p>Monsieur <hi>de la Force,</hi> who sat next him, took hold of him, and endeavour'd to help him as well as he cou'd, holding his Handkerchief upon his Wound, from whence the Blood gushed out in great quantity, but all in vain; for he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready gone. Thus lamentably died this brave Prince.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48812:14"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS Upon the GOVERNMENT OF LEWIS XIII. Sirnamed the <hi>JƲST.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. I. <hi>Concerning the Government of</hi> Mary de Medicis, <hi>Queen Regent of</hi> France, <hi>in the Minorit of</hi> Lewis <hi>the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IMmediately after the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, his Queen <hi>Mary de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis</hi> was declared Regent or Protectress of the Kingdom during the Minority of <hi>Lewis</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48812:15"/>the Thirteenth, notwithstanding all the Opposition of the Princes of the Blood, who disputed and opposed her Authority. The first Action of her Government, was the terrible Execution of <hi>Ravaillac.</hi> But since it is described at large in the Histories of those times, I will only mention two Particulars that they are silent in. The first is, That this abominable Parricide was approved of at the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and some there are that affirm, his Picture was placed among those that are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Martyrs. The other, That the Judges that took his Examination and Confession, were so troubled and frighted at his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, that they took an Oath of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresy among themselves, never to disclose the particulars that this abominable Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster had discovered. Which has afforded great matter of enquiry to those that were curious and inquisitive in this Affair: But whenever any enquiry was made of the Judges themselves, they returned no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, but lifted up their Shoulders, and hung down their Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p>Among other of <hi>Ravaillac</hi>'s Answers, once he spoke to the <hi>Mareschal de la Force,</hi> and told him, <hi>Sir, you have twice hindred me from killing the King:</hi> And, indeed this Lord has since said, <hi>That he very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, that he thrust him by once when he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48812:15"/>was approaching the King's Person, observing something very Fatal, and Malevolent in his looks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the beginning of the Queens Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Princes, and great Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Cabal, and make Parties against her. She had several secret Meetings at <hi>Paris;</hi> but their Projects taking Wind, the Duke of <hi>Bouïllon,</hi> who was of the Party, and one of the most refined Politians of his time, advised them all to leave <hi>Paris;</hi> not at all doubting but the Queen would se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them all, to prevent a Civil War. The Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the rest Answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and said, <hi>The Queen durst not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a thing of that Consequence. Very well, Gentlemen, you may do as you please, but, as for me, I'll immediately get a Horse-back, and ride away to save my self in Silk-stockings; but if they make me wear out a pair, I swear, I'll make them wear a</hi> 100 <hi>pair of Boots.</hi> And so it proved; for the Queen no soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had intimation of his flight, but she ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and imprisoned the Princes, which did not contribute a little to the Establishment of her Power; though it was then said as a Jest, or Quibble, <hi>That the Queen must needs be very ill, since she was not able to take her Bouïllon,</hi> which signifies <hi>a mess of Broth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this minority of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48812:16"/>Queen Regent, who Governed all things, only acted as she was managed by the the Marquis of <hi>Ancre</hi> her great Favourite. It was usually said then, that <hi>France,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a Ship, was very safe, since it was at <hi>Ancre;</hi> to which was applied this Verse of <hi>Virgils Aeneis, lib.</hi> 6.</p>
               <q>Anchora de prorâ jacitur, stant littore puppes.</q>
               <p>But others there were, who malicious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Explained this Verse, to the scandal of the Queens Person; who, to say truth, only liv'd for <hi>Mons. d'Ancre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During this <hi>Regence,</hi> when the Princes and great Men were either Imprisoned, or Banished, the Governors of the Provinces, who were all very affectionate for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Service, were retired to their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral commands, to keep all things in Peace and Quietness. At this time it hapned, that the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Moors,</hi> who before had enjoyed Peace and Liberty; but for the horrible Crimes, real, or imaginary, that they committed against the Glory of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, were expelled by the King of <hi>Spain</hi> out of his Dominions. There went cross the Strait of <hi>Gibraltar</hi> into <hi>Africk,</hi> about 300000, and over the <hi>Pyrenean hills</hi> the like number; but as these would
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48812:16"/>pass the Mountains, to go through <hi>Bearn,</hi> where the Mareschal <hi>de la Force</hi> was Vice Roy, the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Maranes,</hi> or <hi>Moors</hi> begged liberty of Passage, and offered him a <hi>Ducat</hi> a Head: The Vice Roy, who was very firm to the Orders and Interest of the Queen, would do nothing in it of his own Authority, but dispatch an Express to her, Declaring how the matter stood, to know her Pleasure, and if she would make her advantage of what they offered, for their Passage. The Queen who had a great value and esteem for him, permitted it, and let him know he might make what advantage he pleased for himself. And every thing was disposed for their passing the River <hi>Pau</hi> in Boats, on the side of which was an empty Boat, into which every Passenger threw in his <hi>Ducat.</hi> As some Thousands were already passed, the Vice Roy came in Person, with some of his chief Followers; and seeing these Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers all in Rags and Tatters, and with miserable Pale and Lean Countenances; he was so much moved to Compassion, that he cry'd out, <hi>I will have none of the Mony of these Unfortunate People, and, as for that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the Boat, share it among you.</hi> This Passage of theirs lasted 2 or 3 Weeks, and they were no sooner out of the bounds of his Government, but the Persons that he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48812:17"/>had sent to convey them, told him, <hi>That all their Rags and Torn Cloaths were quilted full of pieces of Gold; so that they were called the</hi> Gibeonites <hi>of the Age;</hi> and the V. R. very much repented he had imployed his Pitty so ill, and was only laugh'd at at Court for it.</p>
               <p>The Marquis of <hi>Ancre,</hi> as we have said, by the Favour of the Queen Regent, had all the Authority to his Death: But at length <hi>Lewis</hi> growing up, and being sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the Dishonor this <hi>Italian</hi> Favorite did to the Royal Family, he caused him to be killed in the Court of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> in the midst of a 100 Gentlemen, that were about him in manner of a Guard. The Duke of <hi>Vitry</hi> killed him; but before he did it he would have repeated Orders, and very exact, from his Majesty. <hi>Sir,</hi> said he, <hi>is it your absolute Will and Pleasure it should be done?</hi> The King then talked a while privately, with the Marquis of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouïllan,</hi> who was then his chief Favourite; and he came to <hi>Mons. de Vitry,</hi> and said, <hi>The King our Master is not a Prince that delights in Blood; but for the Honour and Good of his Kingdom, he would have his commands Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, if the Marquis of</hi> Ancre <hi>offers to resist, or lay Hand on his Sword;</hi> he then immediately went about it, and Pistolled him. Thus ended the Favour and Life of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48812:17"/>this <hi>Italian,</hi> who while he lived was called the Second <hi>Sejanus;</hi> and, indeed, he was used as the First was, after he was dead; for his Body was drawn Ignominiously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> and torn to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; his Family likewise shared his misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, his Wife being put to Death for a Sorceress.</p>
               <p>The state of Affairs was very wavering for several Years; the Queen being in a great Consternation, the King had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Favourite but the Marquis of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouïllan,</hi> who quite threw himself out by advancing two Gentlemen of <hi>Provence,</hi> who were so very Poor, that they had but one Cloak between them; so that one was forced to stay at home, when the other went abroad. That which gained them the King's Favour, was their great skill in Hawking, which was the chief Pleasure the King took; who, notwithstanding there being introduced by <hi>Mons. de Montpouïllan,</hi> yet they contrived to out him, which was done after this manner.</p>
               <p>There being then Civil Wars in <hi>France,</hi> about Religion, and the Marquis his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being General of the Protestant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in <hi>Guyenne,</hi> as the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> was in <hi>Languedoc. Messieurs de Luynes,</hi> made their advantage of it, and put the King into an ill Opinion of the Marquis, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suading
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48812:18"/>him that it was not fitting he should be the Kings Favourite, whose Father was a Rebel, and an Enemy to the King's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and State. The King being thus wrought upon, called the Marquis of <hi>Montpouïllan, and commanded him to leave the Court, and go to his Father.</hi> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis replied, after this manner; <hi>Sir, after all the Goodness that I have received from you, and so many Favours, Will you reduce me to such a terrible extremity? I have no share in my Fathers Actions, and you your self are a Witness of my Innocence and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I had rather die than take up Arms against your Majesty: Permit me to retire into</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, <hi>or where else you will be pleased to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point; or let me go into</hi> Normandy <hi>and live a retired life.</hi> But the King would hear nothing, and in great Anger, replied, <hi>He would have him get him to his Father.</hi> The young Lord with great Grief obeyed him: And, after he was gone, the elder of the two <hi>Luynes</hi> had such an ascendent over the King, that he was made Constable of <hi>France;</hi> but as he was very malicious, he made the King go in Person, to the War in <hi>Guyenne,</hi> that he might utterly destroy his Benefactor. This young Lord seeing himself so basely used, became like a raging Mad-man, and Fought without any Mercy, or giving Quarter, only he always kept a great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48812:18"/>respect for the King, his Master; which he made appear, upon an occasion when he could easily have taken the King Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner; for he would not suffer his Men to fire upon the Vanguard; but the King being passed, and out of danger, he cut all the Reer in pieces. And for his greater fatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he heard of the Constables Death: As soon as he understood this News, he cryed out, <hi>Now I am content to die, I shall die satisfied;</hi> and so it hapned, for some time after, while he defended the Town of <hi>Tonneins,</hi> making a Sally he routed his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but received a Wound with a Pike, which killed him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. II. <hi>Concerning the Administration of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> Richelieu, <hi>under</hi> Lewis <hi>the Thirteenth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> the Queen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, that advanced Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> and made his Fortune, for he was very much esteemed of by her, whilst he was only Bishop of <hi>Luçon;</hi> but she was very ill requited by him, for the Cardinal having got an absolute Power over the King's
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48812:19"/>Will, he carried matters to that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he made him Banish his Mother, and his Brother, the Duke of <hi>Orleans;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which this Distich was made against the King.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turca <hi>necat Fratrem,</hi> Nero <hi>Matrem, Gallus utrumque;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et quid erit Gallus?</hi> Turca Neróque <hi>simul.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Turk</hi> his Brother, <hi>Nero</hi> his Mother slew;</l>
                  <l>What's <hi>Lewis</hi> then? Both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> too.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Queen Mother retired to <hi>Cologne,</hi> where she died the Third of <hi>July,</hi> 1642. And upon the common story, that the Bodies of the Three Wise Men, the Kings that came from the <hi>East</hi> to Worship and Offer to <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> are in this City; and this poor Queen forsaken, and injured by her own Son; and assisted and maintained by Two Kings, her Sons in Law; this Epigram was made.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tres mihi depulsae donabant munera Reges.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurum Castiliae qui pia Sceptra tenet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui Regit avulsos</hi> Romana <hi>sede</hi> Britannos</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Argentum, Myrrham tu mihi nate dabas.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48812:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though Banish'd, from Three Kings I presents had,</l>
                  <l>And his in Gold, the Pious <hi>Spaniard</hi> made;</l>
                  <l>Silver of him, from <hi>Papal</hi> Bondage free;</l>
                  <l>But Son I had only bitter Myrrh from thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But to return to Cardinal <hi>Richelieu.</hi> It was after the taking of <hi>Rochell,</hi> that his Power was at the highest pitch. For that Town had been often Besieged, but was never taken; and, it was therefore usually called the Maiden City of <hi>France,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the taking of it was generally esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Cardinals Master-piece: The King himself was very often of Opinion, that they should raise the Siege, and not obstinately lye before a Town that was Impregnable. But the Cardinal alone continued firm to his purpose, and publickly said, <hi>That he would either Conquer, or Die before</hi> Rochell.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal acquired Immortal Glory by the <hi>Digue,</hi> or <hi>Mole,</hi> that he made in the Sea, which deprived the <hi>Rochellers</hi> of that assistance they used to receive by Sea; so that they, after all the Defence that was possible to be made, and all that was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to be endured by Man, at last, forc'd by insupportable Famine, they yielded. It was said, this Damm, or Mole, was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48812:20"/>contrived in imitation of that made by <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he Besieged <hi>Tyre,</hi> and joyn'd it to the Main-land. Several about the Court foresaw, that this Town being taken, the Cardinal would quickly be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Master of <hi>France;</hi> and that, being of a very revengeful Temper, he would take off all his Adversaries. <hi>Mons. de Bassompiere,</hi> who was one of them said, <hi>I believe we shall be mad enough to take</hi> Rochell.</p>
               <p>Under the Government of this Cardinal, Wit and Learning were very much valued; he took great satisfaction in advancing Persons that were Learned, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed nobly all Ingenious productions of Wit and Gallantry, especially if they were made <hi>extempore;</hi> whereof we will instance one or two Examples. He had for his Arms two Chevrons, or broken pieces of Wood, so called in Heraldry; and among other Latin Verses, a Poet presented him with, there was this,
<q>Fracta licet sint ligna ferunt fastigia Regni.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He found it so well turned, and it pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him so much, that he gave the Author
<note n="*" place="margin">Dix-mille Francs.</note> a Thousand lb for it: And another time he was Compared to the first Mover of the Sphere, and was called the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48812:20"/>
                  <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> or first Mover of <hi>France,</hi> by this Inscription about his Picture: <hi>Et quo movente caetera moventur, &amp; quo agente agunt, &amp; quo quiescente quiescunt.</hi> With which he was so much taken, that he gave him a very good Ecclesiastical Benefice that presented him with this Encomium, in a Dedication. But this great genius was not only the <hi>Mecaenas</hi> of the Learned, but he took a great deal of Pleasure in Criticising their Works, but chiefly <hi>French</hi> Poets; and this is an instance, when meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with these Verses, describing Ducks in the Water.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>La Canne s'humectoit dans la bourbe de l'eau,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>D'une voix enroüée &amp; d'un battement d'aîle</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Animoit le Canard qui languit auprés d'elle.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With a hoarse quacking noise, and Wings fluttering high,</l>
                  <l>She rouses the Drake that swims slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gishly by.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Cardinal, out of a piece of Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisme, said to the Poet, <hi>Sir, you would have done better to put</hi> Barbotoit, <hi>that stirs up, rather than rouses; it would be much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48812:21"/>and I advise you to put it in.</hi> The Poet, out of Humor, replied, <hi>My Lord, I won't change, nor alter my Piece, what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten I am sure is very well writ:</hi> But, says the Cardinal, <hi>Sir, I'll reward you very well, only satisfie me in it.</hi> The Poet very positively, and much in love with his own Judgment, flat and plainly refused him, which angred the Cardinal to that degree, that he used him like a Rogue, and caused him to be thrust out of Doors. But just upon this comes in an Embassador from a Forreign Prince, who very Ingeniously Complemented his Eminence, in Extolling the great Power he had in <hi>France;</hi> but he interrupted him with these Words, <hi>No, my Lord Embassador, do not think so, my Power is not so great as you imagine; for a little nasty Poet, do whatever I could, would not so much as put one Word instead of another, by which, you may easily see my Authority is not so great as it is esteemed.</hi> The worst quality that this Cardinal had, was to destroy, without Mercy, his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all those that opposed his Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, or the establishment of his Fortune. This was the only reason, why he caused the Marshal <hi>de Marillac,</hi> without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cause, and the Duke of <hi>Montmorency,</hi> who was the Love and Joy of <hi>France,</hi> Monsieur <hi>St. Marc &amp; de Thou,</hi> who never Trangressed their Duty. And this <hi>Grotius</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48812:21"/>learned by Remark in his Abridgement of the Cardinals Life and Death, just after his decease; <hi>Marillia cum summa injustitia, Montmorencium summo jure, Sanmarcium jure cum injuria, Thuanum, jure vel injuria, capite plecti voluit.</hi> As for Monsieur <hi>Marillac,</hi> it was openly declared through all <hi>France,</hi> that his Innocence was wronged, and that the Cardinals Jealousy alone was this great Man's Executioner. In regard of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Montmorency,</hi> Marshal and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of <hi>France,</hi> it was confessed, that the Lyon and Mars of <hi>France</hi> was destroyed, to her irreparable loss.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars est mort, il n'est plus que poudre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et ce grand Phoenix des Guerriers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sous une forêt de Lauriers</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N'a sçû se garentir du foudre:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sa trame vient d'étre coupée,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Au regret de tout l'Univers:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Il ne vit plus que dans nos Vers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et par ce qu'a fait son Epée.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Toy qui les lis, &amp; ne sçait pas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>De quelle façon le trépas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Emporta cette Ame guerriére,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ces deux Vers t'en feront savant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>La parque l'a pris par derriére;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N'osant l'attaquer par devant.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48812:22"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Mars of <hi>France</hi> is dead, we see</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Montmorency</hi> is no more;</l>
                  <l>Nor was the Hero Thunder free,</l>
                  <l>Although he Groves of Laurel wore.</l>
                  <l>Whilst all Mankind his Fortune grieves,</l>
                  <l>That his untimely Race is run;</l>
                  <l>He only in our Verses lives,</l>
                  <l>And by what his Sword has done.</l>
                  <l>Reader, if thou fain wou'dst know</l>
                  <l>How he received this dire disgrace;</l>
                  <l>Behind him came the fatal blow,</l>
                  <l>Death durst not look him in the Face.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Monsieur <hi>St. Marcs &amp; de Thou,</hi> after Process made against them at <hi>Lyons,</hi> were Sentenced to be Beheaded; the first, for Caballing with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and some Princes, not only against the King's, but against the Cardinal's Life; who had raised him, and made him the King's Favourite: The latter, for not revealing his Friends Secret, although he endeavoured to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade him from that fatal design; which occasioned this Epigram.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Morte pari periere duo, sed dispari causa,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fit reus iste tacens, fit reus ille loquens.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48812:22"/>
                  <l>Both died alike, but for a different rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</l>
                  <l>One for concealing, t'other for speaking Treason.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But, yet the cause of Monsieur <hi>de Thou</hi>'s Death, is not to be imputed to the Crimes he was accused of, but to some passages in his Fathers History, where one of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Richelieu</hi>'s Ancestors is represented, as one of the wickedest of Men, as may be seen in the 633, 639, and 640 pages of that excellent History. They say, this Cardinal was by these innocent Persons, cited to appear before the Tribunal of God. When he died, he was buried in the <hi>Sorbonne;</hi> and Monsieur <hi>de Thou</hi>'s Sister seeing the Cardinal's Tomb there, she cryed out in the Words of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, in the Scripture: <hi>Domine si fuisses bîc, Frater meus non fuisset mortuus:</hi> O Lord, if thou hadst been here, my Brother had not died. It was observed, that Monsieur <hi>de Thou</hi> was put to Death, upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of Monsieur <hi>St. Marcs,</hi> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Defiat;</hi> this was said upon it, <hi>Si par un seul Fiat, tout a éte fait, par un seul De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiat</hi> Thou, <hi>ou tout a eté defait.</hi> The Quibble does not hold in English, nor may be is it worth while, if by one <hi>fiat,</hi> all things
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48812:23"/>were made, so by one <hi>Defiat, Thou</hi> or <hi>tout,</hi> all was destroyed.</p>
               <p>The vindicative Temper of this great Polititian was predominant in all his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but this is an Instance observable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. The King (whose absolute govering Genius the Cardinal was) being very sick, and given over by the Physitians, Monsieur <hi>de Guise, Montmorency</hi> and <hi>Bassompierre,</hi> who aimed at governing the Kingdom, if once they could take off the Cardinal, were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing how they should get rid of him, the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> first declared his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which was this, <hi>Do not let us kill the Cardinal, because he is a Prince of the Holy Church; let us send him to</hi> Rome <hi>to say his Breviary, or his Prayers, with the other Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Montmorency,</hi> who was of a more violent Temper, said, <hi>They must take off his Head, as an Enemy to publick Peace and the Common Good;</hi> but said <hi>Bassom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pierre, Let him not be banished the Kingdom, nor sent to</hi> Rome; <hi>for there he will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Caballing and Contriving Mischief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> France; he added besides, That <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia abhorret à sanguine,</hi> The Church ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred Blood, <hi>and that by no means he shou'd be beheaded; but it was fit he should be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned in the</hi> Bastille, <hi>and there he might have time and leisure enough to write good Books, that might instruct Mankind.</hi> The
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48812:23"/>Cardinal, who had his Spies listning every where, understanding their Project, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make them suffer what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd for him. For the King recovering, and he being greater than ever; he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them after the same manner; for the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> he caused to be banished, and commanded to retire to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he stay'd till the Cardinal's Death. The Duke of <hi>Montmorency</hi> was beheaded. As for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Bassompierre,</hi> he laid him up in the <hi>Bastille,</hi> and being more a Man of Wit than Action, he had time and leisure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough there to write, what Books he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; for there he remained till the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal died, as the Verses note that were made upon his Anagram.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FRANCOIS de BASSOMPIERRE</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FRANCE,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">I go out of my Prison.</note>
                     <hi>Je sors de ma PRISON.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enfin sur l'arriere-saison</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>La fortune d'Armand s'accorde avec la mienne;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France, je sors de ma prison.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quand son ame sort de la sienne,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France</hi> know my Fortune, and <hi>Armand's</hi> agree</l>
                  <l>When I regain my long wish'd Liberty,</l>
                  <l>His eager Soul is from his
<note n="*" place="margin">Prison.</note> Body free.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:48812:24"/>
               <p>So sure it is that <hi>Richelieu</hi> never spared any ones Life that attempted his, of which we will give an extraordinary Example. The Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> the King's Brother, was the Cardinals mortal Enemy; and Monsieur <hi>de Puylaurent,</hi> who was his Favourite, and turned him as he pleased, encouraged this hatred, and made him take a resolution to stab him with his own Hand. The Prince going to the Cardinal upon this design, no sooner approach'd him, but his Nose fell a bleeding; upon which, instead of doing him any harm, he told him what his intention was, and begged his Pardon. Upon this, the Cardinal took his measures, and as a seeming instance of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Favour to <hi>Puylaurent,</hi> he Married him to his Niece, Madam <hi>de Vieupont,</hi> but 'twas only with design to ruin him, as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately he did; for in the midst of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities and Rejoycings that were made for the Wedding, he arrested him Prisoner, and sent him to the <hi>Bastille,</hi> where some time after he was poysoned by a Priest in a mess of Broth. As soon as ever he had swallowed it, the Priest said to him, <hi>Sir, you must Confess your Sins;</hi> upon which, throwing the Porringer at his Head, he cryed out, <hi>Wicked Villain! What did ever I do to thee?</hi> However, he Confessed and died a little after.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48812:24"/>
               <p>After the Cardinal had dispatched his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, fluttered he was then at the top of Fortunes-wheel, and was the sole Governor of the Kingdom; but because he always took care, as much to maintain his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as he did to obtain it; he excluded all those that were capable of opposing his Ambition, from the greatest Offices and Commands; and indeed in his time we find that the chiefest Military Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were in the Hands of Church-men. As an Epigram tells us, made upon this occasion.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un Archevêque est Admiral,</hi> De Bordeaux.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un gros Evêque est Corporal,</hi> De Chartres.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un Prelât Président aux Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieres,</hi> De Nantes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un autre a des troupes guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieres,</hi> De Mande.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un Capucin pense au Combat,</hi> P. Joseph.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un Cardinal a des Soldat,</hi> De la Valette.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Un autre est Généralissime;</hi> De Richelieu.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France, je crains qu'icy bas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ton Eglise si magnanime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Milite &amp; ne triomphe pas.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When an Arch-bishop's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, <hi>A. B. of Bord.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And a fat Bishop's Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; <hi>Bp. of Chartres.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48812:25"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bp. of Nantes.</hi> One Governor of the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers made,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bp. of Mande.</hi> Another Armed Troops does lead.</l>
                  <l>We see an humble Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Father Joseph.</hi> His pious mind to Wars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Card. de la Valette.</hi> Souldiers obey one Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Richelieu</hi> is General.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France,</hi> of her War - like Church, may justly vaunt,</l>
                  <l>Though it Triumphs not, yet 'tis Militant.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Though ever since <hi>Henry</hi> IV. it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been the design of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> to restore the Monarchy to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Glory, and extend it to the ancient bounds: Yet, Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi>'s grand design was to Unite the two Religions, that were professed by the <hi>French.</hi> To bring this about, he made use of Father <hi>Joseph,</hi> a Capuchine Fryar, that was his Confessor, who Communicated this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his, to the chief Ministers of the Protestant Religion in <hi>France,</hi> and came to this Agreement with them, That if the Protestants would comply with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ceremonies of the Roman Church,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48812:25"/>she would be contented with, and leave them the Confession and Articles of Faith, that were owned by the Protestants; but this project came to nothing, by reason of the Capuchines Death.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Joseph</hi> was, by every one, counted a very wicked Fellow, and being buried by another Fryar, called F. <hi>Angell;</hi> this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph was made for him.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Passant, n'est ce pas chose étrange,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>De voir un Diable auprés d'un Ange?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do you think it not strange, all you that pass by,</l>
                  <l>That a Devil so near, an Angel should lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And because he died suddenly, without Confession, this other was made upon him.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sous ce Tombeau git un bon Pére,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui eut tant de discretion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Que pour être bon Secrétaire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Il mourut sans Confession.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A cunning Fryar here lies below,</l>
                  <l>Great was his secrecy, great his discretion;</l>
                  <l>Who because a close Statesman himself he would show,</l>
                  <l>He march'd out o' th' World without any Confession.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48812:26"/>
               <p>It's said, that after he was dead, they found under his course Fryars Gown a very fine Satin sute of Clothes. At that time the City of <hi>Brisac,</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> was beseiged, and very near taking; Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> instead of Comforting and Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Capuchine, then in the Agony of Death, bawled out in his Ear, as loud as he was able, <hi>Courage, Father</hi> Joseph Brisac <hi>is taken.</hi> But this good News did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him from his Apoplexy, for a few Moments after he died; upon which was made this Distich.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Itè cucullati, vobis si purpura ridet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fungitur inferni Munere Pontificis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No wonder Fryars, that Prelats mock you, know</l>
                     <l>'Tis what th' Infernal Pope will do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The Cardinal was very Sick when he cut off the Heads of Monsieur <hi>de St. Marcs</hi> and <hi>de Thou,</hi> so that by the Doctors Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he was carried into Houses through the Windows, which verified <hi>Nostrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>'s Prophecy, which was in these Words.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48812:26"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Mons. <hi>Saint Marcs</hi> is also written <hi>Cinque Marcs,</hi> or five Marks which is 40 Ounces.</note> Quand le Bonnet Rouge passera par fenestre,</l>
                  <l>A quarante onces on coupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra la tête.</l>
               </q>
               <p>When the Red-cap shall go through the Windows, Forty Ounces shall be beheaded.</p>
               <p>It is worth noting, that Queen <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> these Noble Gentlemen, and Cardinal <hi>Richelieu</hi> died all in the same Year; and King <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. lived so little a while after him, that this was applied to them, <hi>Quemadmodum se in vitâ dilexerunt, Ita in mortè non sunt separati.</hi> However, the King who was sensible that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, even Usurped his Authority; at the News of his Death, he cryed out, <hi>Now I am King again.</hi> Several Persons were of opinion, that the Cardinal, to be revenged of the King, who was consenting and assisting to the last Conspiracy against him, had given him a slow Poyson, whose Death he foresaw would happen at the same time that it did, which was conjectured by a very Eloquent Discourse, which was found among his Papers after his Death; in which he thanked the three Estates of the Kingdom, because out of the great esteem and value they had for him, they had chosen him Regent of the Kingdom.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48812:27"/>For it is certain that the Cardinal was esteemed the very Genius of <hi>France,</hi> and was reverenced like a Deity; a proof of which is, that, when <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. making a solemn entrance into St. <hi>Quintin</hi> in <hi>Picar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> with his Brother the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> and the Cardinal going in the middle of them; there was presented to his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence a large Flag, or Standard, in which the King, Duke, and Cardinal were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, drawn to the Life, with these Words in great Letters,
<q>
                     <l>Francia Gaude,</l>
                     <l>Numine trino Quid libet aude.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The extraordinary Ambition of this Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, may be observed in his management to his Officers and Servants. He gave all of them, according to their Degrees and Merits, Estate enough to live at ease and quiet all their Days, but upon Condition, that they should not serve any Lord, or Prince whatsoever ever after; which was looked upon by all <hi>France,</hi> as one of the greatest pieces of Ambition that ever was. The Cardinal was no sooner dead, but every one was writing something upon him, reflecting upon his Person, or Conduct; but they were all out done by the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Grotius,</hi> who, in an incomparable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48812:27"/>Epitaph gives us the Description, and Epitome of this great Man's Life.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Epitaphium.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Sta Viator, quo properas?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid usquam videbis hîc tegitur,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joannes Armandus Du Plessis de</hi> Richelieu.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clarus origine, Magnus ingenio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fortuna eminentissimus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sacerdos in Castris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theologus in aula,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Episcopus sine plaebe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cardinalis sine titulo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rex sine nomine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unus tamen omnia:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Naturam habuit in numerato.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Foelicitatem in Consilio.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aerarium in peculio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Victoriam sub signis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Socios in procinctu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amicos in Carcere.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cives in servitute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In hoc uno miser,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod omnes miseros fecit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tam saeculi sui tormentum quàm orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poëta purpuratus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui scena mundus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gloria Siparium</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Regia casa corugium fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Afflixit Hispaniam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cepit Flandriam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48812:28"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turbavit Lotharingiam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vastavit Germaniam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fovit Angliam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lusit Europam;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Post regnum testamento suis distributos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dissipatos Principes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobilitatem ferro, ac suppliciis exhaustam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paupertatem populo imperatam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cum fatiscente corpore animum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Grandioribus consiliis aegrè vegetaret,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Derepentè spirare desiit, &amp; timeri.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O fluxa mortalitas!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quàm tenue momentum es!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inter omnia &amp; nihil</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortui corpus rheda extulit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secuti pedites, equitesque</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Magno numero,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faces praetulerunt Ephaebi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Crucem nemo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quia currus vehebat publicam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inter Theologos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Situs ingens disputandi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Argumentum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fidem Regi servavit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spem vivis reliquit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charitatem ab haeredibus abstulit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quo migravit, Sacramentum est,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoc te volui Viator hic te metire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et ab eundo roga</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ut vixit in bello, sic requiescat in Pace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48812:28"/>
               <p>This is thought a great piece of Arrogance to Translate, and indeed the Beautiful Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal cannot well be copied in any other Language.</p>
               <p>This is another, playing upon his Name.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic jacet Armandus ni nos vexasset Amandus</l>
                  <l>Hic jacet Armandus si non armasset Amandus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This passage of <hi>Isaiah</hi> was ingeniously ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic jacet Vir qui conturbavit terram,</l>
                  <l>Qui concussit Regna.</l>
                  <l>Qui posuit orbem desertum &amp; urbes ejus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struxit.</l>
                  <l>Vinetis ejus non aperuit carcerem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In short, he was not spared at all after his Death, for there were Epitaphs made that accused him of keeping, and lying with his own Neice; whereof these are some.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vous tous qui admirez les faits de</hi> Richelieu,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ne mettez plus ainsi vôtre ame à la torture,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pour sçavoir s'il étoit Homme, Ange, Diable, ou Dieu;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sa Niéce vous dira quelle étoit sa nature.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All you that <hi>Richelieu</hi>'s Deeds admire,</l>
                     <l>Your Fancies you need no longer Fire.</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:48812:29"/>
                     <l>To know if he were Angel fiend, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Creature;</l>
                     <l>For his Neice can best give account of his Nature.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <head>Autre.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dessons ce tombeau git icy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L'Oncle, le Pére &amp; le</hi> Mary.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Icy git dessous ce tombeau,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Le Cardinal, la bonne piéce,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On en eut fait un Saint Nouveau,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S'il n' eût point baisè sa Niéce.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <l>This very Tomb here does inclose</l>
                  <l>The Uncle, Father, and the Spouse;</l>
                  <l>Even Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> who might have been Sainted,</l>
                  <l>If he had not so well with his Neice been acquainted.</l>
                  <l>He Miracles wrought with his handsome Relation,</l>
                  <l>'Tis a wonder! they hindred his Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And it was generally believed he had had two Children by her, who were sent into the Isle of <hi>Broüage,</hi> though the following Epitaph tells us the contrary.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48812:29"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Icy git ce grand Cardinal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui ne fit jamais que du mal;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>C'est un honeur de la nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qu'il est mort sans progeniture.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here the great Cardinal lies still,</l>
                  <l>Who, whilst he liv'd did nothing but ill:</l>
                  <l>We're beholding to Nature that he's last of his kind,</l>
                  <l>And has left us none of his vile race be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>That which was made upon his designs upon the Papacy is something indecent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but to comprehend it the better, we must understand that the disease he died of was a horrible Gangreen in his Fundament, when he had just taken Physick, and was then upon the Close-stool. It is not possible, or it may be not reasonable to express the Quibbles and Equivocations of another Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in ours, where all such stuff is count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as really it is, the worst way of triffling; but the sence of our Author is something to this purpose.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cy git, qui d'un esprit pervers,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sans se souvenir qu'il fuit homme,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Se promettoit tout l'Univers</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Par la possession de</hi> Rome;</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:48812:30"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Il aspiroit par vanité</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A quoy il n'êtoit pas utile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dieu voulant que la Papauté</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aux Fideles servît d'azile;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Car sur un si mauvais &amp; pourri fondement,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L'Eglise se fut renversée,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et en chiant à tout moment.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Du S. Siége il eût fait une chaise percée.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An Ambitious vile Wretch lies under this Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Who design'd to rule all by possessing of <hi>Rome:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But his purposes quite were defeated he found,</l>
                  <l>For the Church cou'd not stand on such rotten Ground.</l>
                  <l>And he shiting at all times, and every where</l>
                  <l>Wou'd have made a Close-stool of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Chair.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The following Verses taxed him with an intent to Usurp the Kingdom, which has some kind of relation to his Harangue he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed for the Three Estates, found among his Papers after his Death.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Martel, Capet &amp; Du Plessis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Se sont trouvez tous trois assis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dessus le Trône de la</hi> France;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Les deux premiers l'ont usurpé,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:48812:30"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Au troisiéme il est échapé,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Graces à Dieu &amp; son Eminence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Three Men their Fortune did advance,</l>
                  <l>To rule the mighty Realm of <hi>France;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Martel, Capet</hi> and <hi>Richelieu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The first Two took it as their due:</l>
                  <l>To th' Throne, the 'other did not climb;</l>
                  <l>We only may thank God and him.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. III. <hi>Concerning the Life and Temper of</hi> Lewis <hi>the Thirteenth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEwis</hi> the Thirteenth being born under the Celestial Sign of <hi>Libra,</hi> or <hi>Ballance,</hi> the Emblem of Justice; was Sirnamed the <hi>Just,</hi> for many reasons; his conduct being always accompanied with Justice. It is said, that the greatest Happiness this King ever had, was to meet with that powerful and admirable Genius of <hi>Richelieu,</hi> to govern his Kingdom, who was not only a true French-Man, but one that had an ardent passion of augmenting his Princes Glory. And, it's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that this Mans Memoires are the Model of all the great Enterprises, that are aimed at in our Days. As for the King himself, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of his mean Spirited inclinations, he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48812:31"/>was very little esteemed by his People. One of his notable diversions once was, that he made a great Pasty, which he filled with the flesh of Woolf, Dog, Fox, and several other unclean Creatures; but he seasoned, and made it taste excellent well; upon this he made a splendid Treat for the Queens Maids of Honor, and the Kings Pasty was placed upon the Table, in the middle of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral good dishes of Meat: The Ladies, for the Credit of the Kings Royal Pasty made with his own Hands, all eat of it with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Appetite, and found it exquisitely good; the King, all that while, and many Lords of the Court with him look'd at them through a little Window, and found himself such excellent Diversion, that he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the May game of all the Court. He was counted a very cunning Dissembler, for when he had designed to ruin any Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man about him, he always used some Days before to shew them more than ordinary kindness. In this very much resembling that <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, thus mentioned by <hi>Tacitus. Princeps factus naturâ &amp; consuetudine exercitus velare odium fallacibus blandimentis:</hi> So that all those Courtiers who understood any thing of the Politicks, and Management of the Court, when they saw the King Caress any of them more than usually, cryed, <hi>Actum est de illo,</hi> His business is done.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48812:31"/>
               <p>He took great delight in Musick, and Painting pleased him so extreamly, that he drew several Pictures very much to the Life. But his most passionate desire was to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Protestant Religion out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which was not so much encouraged by Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> as by the Jesuits. And in his Reign, that Party was very much weakened by the taking of <hi>Rochelle, St. Jean d'Angely,</hi> with several other Towns. And last of all, by the Capitulation of <hi>Montauban.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before he died, he had resolved to have <hi>Calvin</hi>'s life examined, and a full process made of his Life, Behaviour and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation.</p>
               <p>Being upon his Death-Bed, he sent for those of the greatest Quality in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who were of the Protestant Religion, as Marshal <hi>Chatillon,</hi> Monsieur <hi>de la Force,</hi> &amp;c. and applied himself to them in these Words, <hi>Cousins, you have always shewed so much Zeal and Fidelity for my Service, that I must thank you most affectionately; and the more to pay my acknowledgments to you, I conjure you to return to your Mother Church, which you quitted at the persuasion of some Arch-Hereticks. Indeed it is true, I have born with the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in these Sentiments, but do not think that ever any of my Successors will have the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence for you, as to suffer it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Curious Observers have found, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48812:32"/>all this Prince's Favourites have either been Disgraced, or made Tragical ends. The first, was the Marquis of <hi>Montpouïllan,</hi> the second, the Constable <hi>de Luynes,</hi> who died as the Marquis did in <hi>Guyenne,</hi> at the War made for Religion. But the blind Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servance that this good King always had for Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> occasioned this Epitaph.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cy git le bon Roy nôtre Maître,</l>
                  <l>Louïs treize de ce nom,</l>
                  <l>Qui fut vingt ans valet d'un Prêtre,</l>
                  <l>Et pourtant acquit grand renom;</l>
                  <l>Ouy chez autruy, mais chez luy non.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The good honest King our Master lies here,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth of that name,</l>
                  <l>Who was slave to a Priest above 20 year;</l>
                  <l>And yet he gained great Fame:</l>
                  <l>But 'twas only abroad they his greatness did tell,</l>
                  <l>For his People at home understood him too well.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:48812:32"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS Upon the GOVERNMENT OF LEWIS XIV.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Administration of Cardinal <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> during the Regency of <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Austria</hi> Queen Mother.</head>
            <p>KING <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. being dead, and the Queen Mother declared Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, 'twas with some difficulty, that Fortune declared her self in savour of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi> He had four Competitours, who all aspired to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry; the Chancellor <hi>Seguier,</hi> the Duke <hi>de la Meilleraye,</hi> who was General of the Artillery, and Father of the Duke of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48812:33"/>
               <hi>Boutilier,</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Des Noyers;</hi> so that the Cardinals station was very waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for some time, but at last he carried it from them all. After the Cardinal was established with an absolute Power, all his Competitors were ordered to leave the Court, that they might give him no occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of suspicion; which went so much to their Hearts, that they almost all died very shortly after, of Grief and Vexation. A little after this, the Cardinal had a difference with Monsieur <hi>de Beaufort,</hi> he that was lost at <hi>Candia;</hi> and he was near outing and ruining the Cardinal, but he having so great an ascendent over the Queen, Triumphed over all his adversaries; and, as for this Prince he caused him to be sent to the Castle of <hi>Vincennes,</hi> where he was kept Prisoner, till he escaped out of it. An Astrologer of <hi>Paris,</hi> foretold the very Day that Monsieur <hi>de Beaufort</hi> should creep out of Prison; the Cardinal having notice of it, sent for the Astrologer that Day he affirmed the Prince should get out of Prison, and spoke to him after this manner; <hi>Well Mr. Astrologer, your Predictions are nothing else but vain Fables, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> de Beaufort <hi>is still Confined, and strictly Guarded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, answered he, <hi>I will be bound to burn all my Books, and your Eminence shall hang me, if it does not come to pass the Day I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48812:33"/>it is come indeed; but it is not past.</hi> And, in effect, a few Hours afterwards Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Beaufort,</hi> with the help of some Ropes that had been privately sent him, got out of a Window, and let himself down into the Castle Ditch, where he had a good Horse ready for him, and quickly escaped out of danger, to the astonishment of all the Court, and the great Reputation of the Astrologer. However, the Cardinal remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Master, notwithstanding all the vigorous opposition of the Princes against him, for his extraordinary cunning, with the Queens firm Resolutions, kept him safe in spight of all their endeavours. But the greatest dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that ever the Cardinal was in, was when he was solemnly condemned by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> who declared him a publick Enemy, and disturber of the Peace of <hi>France;</hi> and set a Price of 50000 Crowns upon his Head, for any one that should bring him dead, or alive.</p>
            <p>So that he was constrained to give way to the Storm, and quit the Kingdom; and then the People used to say of him, <hi>Mazarine, pack up your Bag and Baggage and be gone; our Queen is come into her right Sences again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rise of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> was an extraordinary act of Fortune, for he was a very inferior Man of Business; but his address and success in several Negotiations, being
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48812:34"/>once known to Cardinal <hi>Richelieu;</hi> he took him near his own Person, and found him so exquisitly cunning, that he usually said, <hi>If I went to cheat the Devil, I would only make use of</hi> mazarine<hi>'s Tricks to do it.</hi> Thus being fix'd in <hi>France,</hi> he became <hi>Richelieus</hi> faithful Slave, who some time after made him a Cardinal like himself; and upon his Death Bed recommended him as the greatest geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and most capable of managing affairs of State. Yet his Condition and Fortune was very uncertain in the first Civil Wars, which were only made upon his account, and had not the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> upheld him, he had been utterly ruined. Of this Prince, the Queen Mother, and Cardinal, it was said, <hi>The Prince undergoes all, the Queen suffers all, and the Cardinal does all.</hi> They relate a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant answer that the Queen made, when they told her that the <hi>Swiss</hi> Army, under Monsieur <hi>d'Erlach,</hi> committed strange dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders; and that some Parties of them were got into a Nunnery, where they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted very great Insolencies against the Honor, and Chastity of the Nuns: The Queen told them, <hi>They are only</hi> Swisses, <hi>they would sooner run into the Cellars, than into the Nuns Bed-Chambers;</hi> and, so made but a trifle of it.</p>
            <p>As Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> was assisted by the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> in the first Civil Wars, so
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48812:34"/>was he in the last by Monsieur <hi>Turenne,</hi> who, with a very indifferent Army resisted three powerful Armies, that all opposed the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal; which were, the Prince of <hi>Condes,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Nemours,</hi> and the other of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine.</hi> At last, the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Years of Majority, by his direction he Reigned very happily seven Years; but at length, so inconstant is Fortune, all that Reverenced and Adored him, became his mortal Enemies; and the greatest part of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> made a Party against him, and banished him the Kingdom. He then was forced to give way to the Tempest, till other Troubles embroiling the State were over, and then he passed through the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part of <hi>France,</hi> with an Army that he brought to the Kings assistance, and met his Majesty at <hi>Poitiers.</hi> So that after all their endeavours, he still kept his Post, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Mens Opinion died in Peace and Honor; after his death this Distich was made on him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Occubuit tandem victrix haec purpura, nempe</l>
               <l>Docta fuit bello vivere, pace mori.</l>
            </q>
            <p>All his management in Government, was very like that of Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> unless it were that he aimed more at the Lives of People, than their Estates; and the other,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48812:35"/>quite contrary, was so wedded to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, that to Inrich Himself and Family, he reduced <hi>France</hi> to extream Misery and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; and, therefore after the death of these two Ministers of State, it was said,
<q>
                  <l>Fata duos rapuere Duces Regnique Ministros;</l>
                  <l>Abstulit ille bonos, abstulit ille bona.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And against Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> were these Words, Julius Caesar <hi>Gallias subegit, quas</hi> Julius Mazarinus <hi>expilavit;</hi> which were explained by an Epitaph to this Sence.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ci git que la goute foüilla,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Depuis les pieds jusqu'aux épaules.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Jules <hi>non qui conquit les</hi> Gaules,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mais celui qui les dépoüilla.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here <hi>Julius</hi> lies, who did his Power ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance;</l>
               <l>Not he that Conquer'd, he that plundred <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>And indeed he sent so vast a quantity of Treasure into <hi>Italy,</hi> that his Father amazed to see so much Gold, once cryed out, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it rains pieces of Gold in</hi> France. Besides what was sent abroad, he left prodigious Estates to his Nephews and Nieces, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Duke of <hi>Mazarine</hi> the Duke
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48812:35"/>of <hi>Meillerayes</hi> Son, whom he made his Heir upon condition, that he should Marry one of his Neices, (the Dutchess of <hi>Mazarine</hi> now in <hi>England</hi>) and quit his own Name to take that of <hi>Mazarine.</hi> The mighty Riches, whether well, or ill, gotten by the Cardinal, occasioned this Epigram.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>J'entens que l'un dit force mal</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Des desseins, des faits &amp; des veilles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>De ee célébre Cardinal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et que l'autre en dit des merveilles;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pour moi je ne décide rien;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mais quand on compte combien,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L'Immense &amp; l'incroyable somme</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>J'en diray ces quatre mots,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qu'il falloit qu'il fût habille homme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et que nous sommes de grands Sots.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some speak ill of, others praise,</l>
               <l>The actions of the Cardinal;</l>
               <l>I will not decide the Case</l>
               <l>And can say nothing at all.</l>
               <l>But when we his Riches see,</l>
               <l>And how he the Kingdom Rules;</l>
               <l>He a great Man sure must be,</l>
               <l>And we all great Fools.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But we need not wonder at his vast Riches, since he had the absolute disposal of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the Kingdom, all the Kings Minority;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48812:36"/>and, as for the Young King himself, he so carried himself to him, that after his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence died, some body was so bold as to make this punning Epitaph.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dessous ce tombeau git un homme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui valoit moins qu'un sol à</hi> Rome,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mais que l'on a vû dans</hi> Paris,
<note n="*" place="margin">Le Roy, &amp; le P. de Conde.</note>
                     <hi>Val ir plus qu'un double</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Louis.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here lies buried in this Tomb,</l>
                  <l>A Man not worth a Groat at <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But at <hi>Paris</hi> 'twas well known</l>
                  <l>The same Man was worth a Crown.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>His unbounded Authority, the Vexations and Taxes that he loaded the Kingdom with, got him the hatred of the French People. So that he no sooner gave up the Ghost, but every body almost strove to testify how glad they were of it, by making Satyrical Pieces upon him: The smartest and best writ thing, is, this Latin Epitaph, so well known, which gives a full account of this Cardinal.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48812:36"/>
            <q>
               <l>HIC jacet</l>
               <l>Julius Mazarinus,</l>
               <l>Galliae Rex Italus,</l>
               <l>Ecclesiae Praesul Laicus</l>
               <l>Europae Praedo Purpuratus,</l>
               <l>Fortunam omnem ambiit &amp; corrumpit,</l>
               <l>Aerarium administravit &amp; exhausit.</l>
               <l>Civile bellum compressit, sed commovit,</l>
               <l>Regis jura tuitus est &amp; invasit.</l>
               <l>Beneficia possedit &amp; vendidit.</l>
               <l>Pacem dedit aliquando, diu abstulit.</l>
               <l>Hostes cladibus, cives oneribus afflixit,</l>
               <l>Arrisit paucis, irrisit plurimos, omnibus nocuit,</l>
               <l>Negociator in Templo, Tyrannus in Regno,</l>
               <l>Praedo in Ministerio, Vulpes in Consilio,</l>
               <l>Grassator in bello, solus in pace nobis hostis,</l>
               <l>Fortunam olim adversam aut elusit aut cincit:</l>
               <l>Et nostro saeculo vidimus adorari fugitivum,</l>
               <l>Imperare civibus exulem, regnare proscriptum,</l>
               <l>Quid deinde egerit rogas? paucis accipe.</l>
               <l>Lusit, fefellit, rapuit,</l>
               <l>Ferreum nobis saeculum induxit.</l>
               <l>Homo crudeliter Clemens!</l>
               <l>Pluribus tandem morbis elanguit,</l>
               <l>Plures ei mortes coelo irrogante decretas</l>
               <l>Cui Senatus olim, unam decreverat.</l>
               <l>Vincennis se arcibus inclusit moriturus</l>
               <l>Id unum apte fecit Julius, quaesivit carcerem,</l>
               <l>Diu cadentem animum retinuit aegrè reddidit,</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:48812:37"/>
               <l>Sic retinere omnia, nihil reddere didicerat,</l>
               <l>Constanter tandem visus est mori. Quid mirum!</l>
               <l>Ut vixerat obiit simulans.</l>
               <l>Nec morbum quidem ejus novêre qui curabant,</l>
               <l>Hac una fraude nobis profuit, fefellit Medicos,</l>
               <l>Obiit tandem ni fallimur, &amp; pie moriens,</l>
               <l>Regi regnum, Regno Regem restituit,</l>
               <l>Reliquit Praesulibus pessima exempla,</l>
               <l>Aulicis infida consilia,</l>
               <l>Adoptivo amplissima spolia,</l>
               <l>Paupertatem populis,</l>
               <l>Successoribus omnes praedandi artes, materiam nullam,</l>
               <l>Haeredes quos spreverat fecit</l>
               <l>Pauperes quos fecerat, sprevit</l>
               <l>Mirare Viator.</l>
               <l>Id unum habuit ex suo quod daret,</l>
               <l>Nomen suum,</l>
               <l>Pectus illi post mortem apertum est,</l>
               <l>Tunc primum patuit vafrum cor Mazarini</l>
               <l>Quod nec precibus nec lacrymis,</l>
               <l>Nec injuriis quidem moveretur.</l>
               <l>Quaesivimus: Invenêre Medici cor lapideum.</l>
               <l>Quo evasaerit forsitan rogas?</l>
               <l>Sacramentum est.</l>
               <l>Coelum si rapitur tenet,</l>
               <l>Si datur meritis, longe abest;</l>
               <l>Sed quid te moror, Viator?</l>
               <l>Fallit nos iste tumulus;</l>
               <l>Fuge,</l>
               <l>Non est hic sepulcrum Praesulis,</l>
               <l>Sed specus Latronis.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48812:37"/>
            <p>We should never make an end, if we should relate all the Satyrs made upon the Cardinals death, whom every body so hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wished at the Devil; and the following Epigram supposes that the Devil did carry him away.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Le Diable emportant</hi> Mazarine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fait une perte sans seconde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S'il l'eût laissé jusqu' à la fin</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Il eût fait damner tout le monde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Devil was an Ass to seize <hi>Mazarine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It was much to his loss that he took him way,</l>
                  <l>For he'd have help'd him to damn Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</l>
                  <l>If on Earth he had let him but longer stay.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>To end this Chapter; all the good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that <hi>France</hi> received by the Cardinals death, is owing to the Colledge of Physiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who put an end to all her troubles in doing Justice upon this pernicious Minister, according to these lines.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Julius <hi>Occubuit, res esset mira, tot inter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carnifices, furem non potuisse mori.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:48812:38"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julius</hi> is dead, nor is't a wonder, Sirs,</l>
               <l>One Thief shou'd die</l>
               <l>Amidst so many Executioners.</l>
            </q>
            <p>After the Cardinal, and Queen died, <hi>France</hi> began to enjoy the blessings of Peace, which they had been deprived of, almost all the time of the Cardinals Ministry; whose death occasioned this Epigram, in praise of the present King.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Prenez courage, bons François,</l>
               <l>Vous allez vivre heureux sous le meilleur des Roys;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Louis</hi> du grand <hi>Henry</hi> s'en va suivre les traces,</l>
               <l>Il joint l'art de régner</l>
               <l>A celui de charmer;</l>
               <l>A ce coup on le peut nommer,</l>
               <l>Le Maître de toutes les Graces.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Somewhat to this purpose in English.
<q>
                  <l>Courage brave French, the best of Kings will Reign;</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Henry</hi>'s actions he'll revive again.</l>
                  <l>Happy you'll live; in this great Prince are join'd</l>
                  <l>A form Majestick, and a mighty Mind,</l>
                  <l>To charm, as well as govern, all Mankind.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:48812:38"/>And from that time, this Monarch began to shew so vast a genius, and such an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prudence, with so many other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments, that he is accounted the Wonder of this Age.</p>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVAT. II. <hi>Ʋpon the Inclinations, and Disposition of the present King.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis glorious Monarch, who has made so much Noise in the World, in his Youth shewed sufficiently how much he was addicted to his Mistress, and what weakness he was subject to in that kind. And the French, who take a pride to speak with all manner of freedom of their King, (though, at the same time, they have a profound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect for him, firmly fixed in their Hearts) have given him several touches in their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; these following are well enough known.
<q>
                     <l>Bella fugis, bellas sequeris, pugnaeque, repugnas.</l>
                     <l>Et bellatori, sunt tibi bella Thori</l>
                     <l>Imbelles imbellis amas Milesque videris</l>
                     <l>Mars ad opus Veneris, Martis ad arma Venus.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:48812:39"/>[Which consisting in equivocal playing upon Words. I think they'll lose what conceipt is in them, if made English; nor has my Author taken the pains to tag the lines in French.] Yet, though these Verses are true in the first part, they are not so in the second; for the French tell us he had shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wonderful Courage and Valour in all his surprizing actions; his answer therefore in this Distich is very just.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Bellas bellus amo,</l>
                  <l>Martem Mars excita bella</l>
                  <l>Bellator cupio, me quoque bella cupit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And although the two different Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Love and Glory, are in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure incompatible; yet he has managed both of them so well, that he has given just cause of Admiration, to all that consider them. He has had several Mistresses, who were extreamly beloved both before and since he Married the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain, Maria Theresa</hi> of <hi>Austria.</hi> The first Mistress, that he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly owned after his Marriage, was Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de la Valliere,</hi> whom he made Dutchess of <hi>Vaujour,</hi> and loved her so passionately, that the Queen, and Q. Mother grew so very Jealous of his extraordinary Love for that Mistress, that they all used their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to remove it; there was no device, nor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48812:39"/>intrigue but they made use of, even to the interposing the Authority of Father <hi>Anat,</hi> a Jesuit, and the King's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor, to bring about this Design. The good Father did not need much intreaty, to make use of his Authority; and as he was the director of the Kings Conscience, he flattered himself that it would be much easier for him, than for any other to bring him to what they proposed: Whereupon he represented to him, but a little boldly, the Scandal and bad Effects that this way of Life caused, and the ill Impression it made upon the Minds of his People, if his Majesty did not reform; and, at the same time, he seem'd to threaten him with a sharp Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at his next time of Confession. But it hapned that this Discourse was very ill timed, for, as he did not, in the least, follow the Maxims of his Society, which are abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely against such kind of Proceedings; so had he the misfortune to find that he had made his Court very ill, for the King coldly made answer, <hi>That he thanked him kindly for his good Advice, and his past Service; and that henceforward he'd make use of no other Confessor, but the Parson of the Parish.</hi> It's easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guessed how these Words agreed with the poor Confessor, and how the Society cursed him, for being so scurvy a Politician on such an occasion, which he might have improved,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48812:40"/>and made a notable advantage of, if he had but put in practise, what the succeeding Confessors of the same Order have done; for it is most certain, that by their extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary regard to his Majesty, upon the like occasions, they have merited those wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Testimonies of the King's Bounty, that he has, and daily does, gratify the Jesuits with; who, on their side, as a Mark of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, have in return placed the Kings Name, upon the Gate of one of their Colledges, or Houses at <hi>Paris,</hi> against the inviolable Rules of their Order, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn them to put the Name of Jesus on their Buildings; which they took away, as this Distich Complements them.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Abstulit hinc Jesum posuitque insignia Regis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Impia gens, alium non habet illa Deum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They Jesus Name have ta'en from their abode,</l>
                     <l>And plac'd the King's, he only is their God.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>But to return to Madam <hi>de la Valliere;</hi> she was quite outed by Madam <hi>de Montespan,</hi> that succeeded her, who was the Kings Mistress a considerable time.</p>
               <p>They say that the Love <hi>la Valliere</hi> had for the King, (with the Vexation to see her self
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48812:40"/>no longer his Mistress) forced her, contrary to her Inclinations, to turn Nun: Yet these Verses upon her embracing a Religious Life, sufficiently shew she had better motives to it.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deux grands Roys pour m'avoir se sont fait une guerre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dont l'un est. Roy du Ciel &amp; l'autre de la Terre.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Le Roy du Ciel Vainqueur me conduit en ce lieu,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quel bon-heur est plus grand sur la terre &amp; sur l'onde,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Que de me voir aujourd'hui l'Epouze d'un grand Dieu?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D'Amante que j'etois du plus grand Roy du monde.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For me the King of Heaven and Earth have strove,</l>
                     <l>Which of the mighty two should gain my love:</l>
                     <l>But conquering Heaven has brought me to this place.</l>
                     <l>What Earthly Happiness can mine sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass?</l>
                     <l>Since from the greatest Prince's Mistress, I</l>
                     <l>Am now become Spouse, to the Deity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>It is observed, that this famous Mistress, in the time of her Favour, was not so Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48812:41"/>as <hi>Montespan,</hi> for she preferred all her Kindred to those Honours, which they would never have arrived to by their own deserts. And her Brother, who was only Count <hi>de Vivonne,</hi> by her procurement was made Duke and Peer, and General of the <hi>Galleys,</hi> and Marshal of <hi>France;</hi> all which Marks of Grandeur make him one of the greatest Persons in the Kingdom, and it is so well known that he was made Marshal by meer Favour; for that once a Person of the first Quality speaking of the difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Marshals <hi>de la Feüillade,</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonne,</hi> made this distinction, that the first was made Marshal by the Sword, and the other by the Scabbard.</p>
               <p>However, it was, Madam <hi>de Montespan</hi> very dextorously managed the advantage she had of being the Kings Mistress, though he had not that Passion for her, as was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly believed; for it's reported, that a Chanoiness, or Nun of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>du Lude,</hi> very often shared his Majesties Favours with her; upon which was made this Epigram.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>La Valliere <hi>étoit du commun,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>La Montespan <hi>de la Noblesse,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et la du</hi> Lude <hi>Chanoinesse,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Toutes trois ne sont que pour un,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:48812:41"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mais sçavez-vous ce que veut faire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Le plus puissant des Potentats?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>La chose paroît assez claire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Il veut unir les trois Etats.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>La Valliere</hi> of common Race,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Montespan</hi> of noble was,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>du Lude</hi> a pious Nun,</l>
                     <l>All for Mistresses are known.</l>
                     <l>If you'd know the reason why</l>
                     <l>These three his Fav'rites he Creates;</l>
                     <l>Our great Prince has a mind to try,</l>
                     <l>To unite the three Estates.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Madamois. <hi>de Fontange</hi> was the Fortunate Lady that succeeded Madam <hi>de Montespan,</hi> but she enjoyed her Happiness not long, dying soon after: She was one that had much more Beauty than Wit. The Prince <hi>de Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sillac,</hi> now called Duke <hi>de la Roche Foucault,</hi> procured her for the King, for which he was made <hi>grand Veneur,</hi> or chief Hunts man of <hi>France,</hi> as these Verses tell us.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sur l'Ocean de la favour,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Marsillac <hi>vogue en plcines voiles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quoi qu'il ne soit pas bon Chasseur,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pour avoir mis la beste dans les toiles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Le Roi l'a fait son grand Veneur.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:48812:42"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Marsillac</hi> with prosperous gales</l>
                     <l>On Favour's Ocean smoothly sails;</l>
                     <l>And, though unskilful in the Trade,</l>
                     <l>Yet he is chief Hunts-man made:</l>
                     <l>Perhaps in it he may excel,</l>
                     <l>Because he finds out Game so well.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Some people ascribe the cause of this lovely young Lady's Death to Madam <hi>de Montespan</hi>'s Jealousy, because the Disease she died of was unusual or unnatural. But sure we ought to believe Madam <hi>de Montespan</hi> was far from committing a Crime of this soul nature, since she was employed in the testifying her Repentance by her pious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations; and to this very day she does the same; for sure it is that she and Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who, at present, perfectly govern the King's Inclinations, were those that first founded the Abbey of St. <hi>Cyr</hi> (scandalously called a <hi>Seraglio</hi>) for the Education of young Ladies, which occasioned this malicious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigram.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deux de Partisannes de Cythere,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>L'ame éprise d'un saint désir,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Du revenu de leurs plaisirs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fondent deux nouveaux Monasteres,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:48812:42"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mais sans le Celeste secours,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Il seront de peu de durée,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>L'assiette en est mal assurée,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Les fondennens branlent toûjours.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Two of fair <hi>Venus</hi> Votaries,</l>
                     <l>Their Souls with holy Zeal inflam'd,</l>
                     <l>Have founded two new Nunneries:</l>
                     <l>With the Revenues by their Pleasure gain'd,</l>
                     <l>But without Miracles, they seem</l>
                     <l>To be but in a piteous taking,</l>
                     <l>Since that which founded and supporteth them,</l>
                     <l>Is continually a shaking.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>But to return to our Grand Monarch; he has besides a very great love for magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Buildings; the <hi>Louvre, Versailles,</hi> and the other places that he has made amazingly glorious, are eternal Monuments of it; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rebuilding of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Verses were made.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Non orbis gentem, non urbem gens habet ulla</l>
                  <l>Urbsve domum, Dominum nec domus ulla parem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Another on the same.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Regia, Rex, Regnum, Tria sunt miracula mundi,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rex animo, Regnum viribus, arte domus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:48812:43"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Kingdom, King, and Palace built so well,</l>
                     <l>In Valour, Strength, and Art, all else excel.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>[Though that was but a slovenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement found upon the white Stone-wall at <hi>Versailles,</hi> where one had plentifully discharg'd his loose Tail against it, and finding it splat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd out into streaks or rays, writ with a Coal under it, <hi>Nec pluribus Impar,</hi> alluding to the Sun the King's Device, with that Motto usually placed upon his Buildings.]</p>
               <p>Yet this great Prince having laid up vast Treasures to supply the expence of his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Designs, has been, though very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Taped, with too much Parsimony; and we have examples of it in some Verses.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Etre fier quand il faut combatre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et en la paix doux &amp; benin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>C'est ressembler à</hi> Henri <hi>quatre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et point du tout à</hi> Mazarine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou art good in time of Peace,</l>
                     <l>And bravely bold at Dangers call;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Harry</hi> the Great th' art like in this,</l>
                     <l>And not <hi>Mazarine</hi> at all.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The others are too bold, and so impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convey'd, that the King found them upon his dressing Table.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:48812:43"/>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu és issu de Race</hi> Auguste,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ton Ayeul est</hi> Henry <hi>le Grand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et ton Pére</hi> Louis <hi>le Juste,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pour toy, tu n'és qu'un</hi> Louis <hi>d'Argent.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou art sprung from a Race <hi>August,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Name of great thy Grand-sir, <hi>Harry,</hi> bore,</l>
                     <l>Thy Father was <hi>Lewis</hi> the Just,</l>
                     <l>For thy part thou art but a
<note n="*" place="margin">A piece of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny called a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Lewis.</note>
                        <hi>Lewis D'or.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The King was amazed when he read the Paper; and, they say, that he promised publickly, not only to Pardon the Author, but to reward him well for his Wit; but it seems he was so far from making himself known, that next Day in the same place were these Words.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu ne le sçaura pas</hi> Louis,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Car j'étois seul quand je les fis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lewis</hi> the thing can ne're be known,</l>
                     <l>I writ it when I was alone.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>However, notwithstanding all these Satyrs upon him, the Humor of the King is to be liberal to Persons of Merit, and Courage;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48812:44"/>and he daily gives such evident Marks of it, that one may as well attempt to obscure the Sun's light, as endeavour to deprive him of the Glory of being Bountiful; that indeed which gave occasion to this Scandal, was the Kings prudence, whose Projects and Designs were so great, as that was applied to him, which was said of <hi>Rome</hi> by the Poet: <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium terris, animos aequabit Olympo.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to go through with his wonderful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises, he was necessitated to lay up great quantities of Money, which is the sinews of War; besides the truest Polititians have ever made a distinction, between the Princes of the Houses of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> and those of the Family of <hi>Valois.</hi> The last being accused not only of too much Liberality, but excessive Prodigality, so far, that <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, the last of that Race, said plainly, <hi>That he would willingly have divided his Kingdom among his Favourites;</hi> and he always rewarded the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices done him very Bountifully, yet he ever testified his trouble, that he could not do it according to their deserts. On the other side the Princes of the <hi>Bourbon</hi> Family, have always been thought to be more inclined to sparing than prosuseness. So that one said well, <hi>That this Verse ought to be altered, Parca manus Belgis, Anglisque Superbia regnat;</hi> and that it should be thus turned, <hi>Parca manus Francis, Anglis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Surperbia regnat.</hi> But to say truth, all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48812:44"/>these are only the effects of the <hi>French</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of censuring.</p>
               <p>The great constancy and firmness to those he loves, is really the true Character of this King; for it's well known, he has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put to Death, or punished any that were his Favourites. It is true indeed, that the Count <hi>de Lauzun,</hi> otherwise Monsieur <hi>de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guelin,</hi> who at first was no more than a poor younger Brother, being arrived to an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary degree of Favour, was ordered to be apprehended three times successively; but still with this reserve, That the King wou'd never do him any harm, which is known to every Body, by the good Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances he is in at present. This Great King has ever been remarkable for his great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, even from his Youth; and has been seen to pull off his Hat, and return a salute to Poor People. And has never offended against the Rules of Civility, or Manners; so that few People ever came from him dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfied. Those that say, he is not Brave, nor has a War-like Soul, have not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered his Actions; for even in his Minority, he was forced to be in Action, and run through all the Provinces of his Kingdom, by reason of Commotions. When he grew up, he performed such great Actions, as have astonished all <hi>Europe,</hi> and have long kept it in suspense, and at a stand!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48812:45"/>
               <head>OBSERVAT. III. <hi>Ʋpon the Life, and Manners of</hi> Lewis <hi>of</hi> Bourbon, <hi>Prince of</hi> Conde.</head>
               <p>THE Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was esteemed a Prodigy of Valor and Courage, and was therefore called the <hi>Lion</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> and in a Picture where he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, armed from Head to Foot, these Words were about it,
<q>
                     <l>Hoc statu, hoc habitu Mars Gallicus ibat in hostem,</l>
                     <l>Condoei ora gerens vultumque animumque.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In effect, Monsieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> who throughly understood his Valor and Worth, often said, <hi>That he thought that never since the Foundation of the French Monarchy was ever seen, a Prince so full of Fire, and Courage, as the Prince of</hi> Conde. But if he was a Man of Execution in War, he had no less a genius in the Cabinet, his Counsels have often been more Successful, than all those of the greatest Polititians of the Kingdom; which made an ingenious Writer say of him,
<q>
                     <l>Et quae beatos efficiunt</l>
                     <l>Condoeus ipse Collecta tenet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:48812:45"/>
               <p>It is said, that when the King had carried on his Conquest against the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> as far as <hi>Utrecht,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> advised the King, immediately to march resoluely to <hi>Amsterdam;</hi> which once taken, he would be absolutely Master of <hi>Holland,</hi> and facilitate his great Design; but Marshal <hi>Turenne,</hi> who had a great Power over the Kings Mind, and Counsels hindered it; apprehending the Dams, that they were ready to cut, would overflow all the Country, which might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the King and all his Army; though those that understood Matters best, said, <hi>That the Prince of</hi> Conde<hi>'s Fire would have been more Advantagious, and Glorious for</hi> France <hi>than</hi> Turennes <hi>Lead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Illustrious Prince was really beloved by all in <hi>France;</hi> but by his changing Sides, Pillaging, and Wasting the Country about <hi>Paris,</hi> as well as several other Provinces, he lost the esteem both of the Parliaments and People.</p>
               <p>In the First Civil War, he vigorously main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s Quarrel, though his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi> was the Head of the other Party, with the Cardinal <hi>de Retz,</hi> who mortally hated <hi>Mazarin;</hi> and it was merrily said.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Le Cardinal de</hi> Retz <hi>a juré par a Crosse,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et le Prince de</hi> Conty <hi>par sa Bosse,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:48812:46"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nous irons tous deux à S.</hi> Germain.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pour prendre</hi> Mazarin.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Cardinal <hi>de Retz</hi> by his Crosier swore,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Conty</hi> by the Crump that on Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he bore,</l>
                     <l>That to St. <hi>Germains</hi> they would go,</l>
                     <l>And setch <hi>Mazarin</hi> whether he would, or no.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>To which the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> replied, <hi>Let that Crook-back Fellow come if he dares, and I'll so thwack his Crump-back with my Sword, that I'll make it flat.</hi> But this Civil War was but like a Fire made of Straw, presently extinguished. And the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> became so formidable, by his haughty Management, that the Cardinal, under the Name of the Royal Authority, Caused him, the Prince of <hi>Conty</hi> his Brother, and the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> his Brother in Law, to be Apprehended, and Imprisoned; their Party before, manifestly encreasing, so that every one almost of Note, used to be asked, <hi>Friend, are you of</hi> Conde, Longueville, <hi>and</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's <hi>Party?</hi> Yet these three Princes had notice given them of the design against their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but they laughed at it, thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves above all attempts. Eight Days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the News of their Imprisonment, as some extraordinary Praises of these Princes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48812:46"/>were read, in the publick News Book, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Marshal <hi>de la Ferté,</hi> who for his great Age, was commonly called the Etern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Father, and was a cunning old Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, in intrigues of the Court. As soon as he heard these excessive Praises, he cried out, <hi>Upon my Honour, in a Weekes time you'll hear these three Princes are clap'd up,</hi> which so hapned exactly. There was then a remarkable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, and a fine piece of Policy Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served of the Queen Regent; she sent for these three Princes, who coming to the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Royal, the Queen came out of her Closet, and received them in her Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber with so many Caresses, that she quite took from them all the suspition of the Danger, that their real Friends had insinuated to them; and after she had talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them a good while, with a great deal of frankness, she retired, saying, <hi>My Lord Cardinal will come to you presently;</hi> the Princes then staying a little, were very much sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised to see Monsieur <hi>de Chabames</hi> very well Guarded, who arrested them in the Kings Name; and as the Prince of <hi>Conty</hi> endeavoured to make a Noise, and some Resistance, he told them, <hi>My Lords, if you Resist, your Business is done.</hi> Upon this, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> gently replied, <hi>Which way must we goe? Monsieur</hi> de la Barre <hi>showing a pair of back Stairs,</hi> said, <hi>You must goe this way.</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:48812:47"/>At the Stairs-foot they found a Coach, in which they were carried, without either Drum, or Trumpet, to <hi>Vincennes,</hi> which was their first Prison; from whence, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after, they were removed to <hi>Havre de Grace,</hi> and at last set free by the Cardinal himself. It is observed of this Prince, that his Temper, in point of Liberality, was very different in his Youth, from what it was afterwards. He then was called the Duke of <hi>Engbuyen,</hi> and to jeer his Father, who was counted the most Covetous Prince in <hi>France,</hi> he used to lay a heap of Gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and take a Handful with one Hand, and put it into his Pocket, saying, <hi>Thus my Father does;</hi> and, then taking it out with t'other hand threw it about to those that passed by, saying, <hi>Thus the Duke of</hi> Enghuyen <hi>does;</hi> but since his Humor was very much altred, for he was afterwards extreamly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to sparing.</p>
               <p>In his Youth he was much a Libertin, and loved to Divert himself by abusing People, there are two passages that are odd enough, then done by him. One is, That one Afternoon coming to <hi>Laon</hi> in <hi>Picardy,</hi> and the Dean of the Church, at the Head of all his Chapter, going in Ceremony to complement him; and as he was making a Speech, whether it was that the young Prince was out of Patience till it were done,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48812:47"/>or that he did not like it, he bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, to get rid of their Company, to ask a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud what a Clock it was; the Canons to shew the earnestness that every one had to inform him, all answering aloud, <hi>My Lord, it's Three;</hi> He replied,
<note n="*" place="margin">Allez-vous donc tous vous faire f—</note>
                  <hi>Goe then all and be Damn'd at Four.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other is the Judge or Mayor of a Country Town, meeting him full butt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to make a Speech to him; as he bowed very low before he began: The Prince, who was very nimble, leap'd over the Magistrate, and when he raised his head, the Prince was behind him, but Mr. Mayor, who wou'd make his Speech let what wou'd come of it, and turning about without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moved at this Caper, bowed again, but not so low, for fear of a second; but the Prince not letting that serve his turn, clap'd his hands upon Mr. Mayor's Shoulders, and over again goes me he; so that poor Fellow was forced to get him gone, without speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word more, in the greatest confusion imaginable.</p>
               <p>This Prince was very much given to his Pleasure, and his Loves; and the Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Youth were notoriously known, and spoke of by every one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:48812:48"/>
               <head>OBSERVAT. IV. <hi>Of some Particularities of the Life of</hi> Henry de la Tour d'Auvergne, <hi>Vis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of</hi> Turenne.</head>
               <p>I Do not pretend here to write the Life of Monsieur <hi>de Turenne;</hi> I only wish, for the sake of his Glory, that some person bolder, and of a capacity fit for so great a Design, wou'd undertake it: But though no one shou'd go about it, yet it is impossible that the Fame of the great Actions done by him shou'd ever be lost. The Transactions of <hi>France</hi> for forty years, are not to be descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed without writing his History. However, by reason for several years together, I have had the honour to be present with him at Actions both of the greatest, as well as smallest consequence; and that Historians often are ignorant of, or neglect very es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Particularities. I will endeavour by some small strokes, concerning both his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story and Person, to leave a true Idea of this great Man to Posterity. That which I shall say to his advantage, ought to be the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believed; because instead of being obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Kindnesses done by him, he utterly ruin'd my Fortune; but this Justice I owe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48812:48"/>him, that he did it without any intention of injuring me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry de la Tour d'Auvergne, Vicomte de Turenne</hi> was of a middle stature, neither fat nor lean. His gate and mien had more of the modest, and timid in it, than any thing that appeared daring and bold. His Hair was of a Chestnut-brown, his Head large, and somewhat bending, his Colour ruddy, his Eyes large, and full of Fire and Life, but covered with thick Eye-brows that join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together. The turn of his Face was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular enough, but yet with a cheerful Air, there was something of Cloudiness joined. So that this mixture made up a Face that had somewhat extraordinary in it, and very difficult to be drawn. When a Child, he seemed to be but of a tender Constitution, nor was he perfectly healthful, till after he was twenty years old: When he was but ten, he stole from his Governour, and after they had long sought, they found him laid asleep upon the Carriage of a Cannon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving, as he said, to lye there all Night: For he had heard his Father, the Duke of <hi>Boüillon</hi> say, that he was perswaded it would be a great while before he wou'd be robust enough to undergo the hardships of War, and therefore this young Prince thought that this would be a Proof to convince him to the contrary. The Duke of <hi>Boüillon,</hi> his Father,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48812:49"/>upon his Death-Bed, called both him and his elder Brother to him, and after many Pious Councels, he recommended Three things to them. The First, Never to forsake the Faith of Jesus Christ, and the profession of the Protestant Religion. The Second, Never to attempt any thing against the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their King. And the Third, Never to shock, in any kind, the Power of the chief Minister, or the great Favourite. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they would infallibly lose their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Estate, and Honor. Yet for all this, both of them acted quite contrary to these Maxims, in all their Affairs, and did not Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve any one of them; for they changed their Religion; fought against their King, and in a Hostile manner declared themselves mortal Enemies, to the Premier Ministers, and chief Favourites; which for some time made them very Unfortunate.</p>
               <p>To return to Monsieur <hi>de Turenne;</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Apprenticeship, in Arms, in <hi>Holland,</hi> under his Uncle the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and we have in a Poet of that time this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic Turennius Heros.</l>
                  <l>Cum Belgis miles primus protulit in Armis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And then he was but a private Souldier; and performed all the Duties of a private
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48812:49"/>Souldier, with such Application, and so much Ardor, that it had like to cost him his Life. He was sent thither, when he was but Fourteen Years old: His inclination to the Wars was extraordinary, and perfectly Natural to him; and he applied himself to Souldiery, with that diligence, that from his very Infancy he seemed to be sensible of no other Passion, but that; so that in a very little time he gained a great Reputation: The Trade of War he followed all his life time, and lived 63 Years. And in the Judgment of every Body, he was thought worthy to come in Competition with the greatest Generals that ever were. He had a good Understanding, and great Natural Parts; but in them there was still observed much more Wisdom and Solidity, than Brightness and Wit. In those Affairs that were of great Consequence, and very Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, he was not long deliberating; and when he had once taken a resolution he kept firmly to it: And what is more, he still saw the End, and understood the Consequence of things better and sooner, than any one beside himself, and could find out ways to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish them. In all the course of his Life, he never had any personal Duel, or Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel; although, especially at first, he served under several that he had no great esteem for; and he has commanded others, whose
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48812:50"/>Dispositions and Humors were very uneasy, and that were yet more uneasy, out of envy and emulation of his Glory: But, besides his never giving Ear to any Tales, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, he despised all disadvantagious Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, that he knew were made concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him at any time; and his Mind being ever imployed about some great Design, he cared very little for any thing which did not really hinder it.</p>
               <p>He never was tempted by any Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise, though Glorious for himself, and of certain Success: If he in the least believed it would hinder the Execution of another Design, more Beneficial to the Kingdom, though not so acceptable to him: For so much did he consider the good of all publick Affairs, that to bring them to a happy Issue, he has very often sacrificed his own For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and Benefit; and sometimes even ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded his Reputation; and far from throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the least misfortunes upon his inferior Officers, that he employed upon Service, he never failed to comfort them, and raise their Courage, when they met with ill Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess. Notwithstanding the many occasions of Choler and Vexation, that he has had from the first time he began to command, he never affronted any one; nor was he ever heard to break out into Anger, in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and, though he was of a mild Temper,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48812:50"/>and extraordinary Patience, yet it appeared that this rare Quality, so constantly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, could not be the effect of his Dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alone, but a Virtue acquired. Once when he was just going to attack the Works of a place Besieged, he found he wanted some Amunition Tools, that were absolutely Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary; and knowing that a Marshal of <hi>France</hi> that commanded there, had more than he needed himself, he sent one of his Guards to him to desire them; who return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very much troubled, relating several rude things the Marshal said, and that he refused to lend them. Monsieur <hi>Turenne</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Officers that were near him, said, <hi>Since he is so Angry, we must make a shift with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Tools, and do as well as if we had them.</hi> After this he Charged, and forced the Lines, and had all the Glory of the Action.</p>
               <p>The last <hi>Flanders</hi> Campagne, some Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers returned from the Army very much incensed against him, though without any reason. In the mean time, he, returning about a Month after them, found that their particular Piques had been improved into a general Disgust against him, so that there was scarce any body at Court that did not take a Pride to complain of him, and Valued themselves upon speaking ill of him. Several of them, and some of the best Quality, caused him to be told of it, and desired to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48812:51"/>adjust Matters, and come to a better Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding: All the answer he made, was, <hi>That he could not come to any adjusting in the case, but that it was sufficient for him to know, that he had never given any of them occasion to be displeased with him.</hi> Yet was not out of hope, but some other time, when perhaps he might give occasion of Complaint, those Gentlemen of the Court would be more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to him; so that afterwards they all came to see him, as if nothing of this kind had hapned, and carried himself to them, as if he had never heard any thing of it. He was incapable of Hatred, but very sensible of Love and Friendship. He was seen to melt into Tears, in the Streets of <hi>Pontoise,</hi> as soon as he heard his Brother, the Duke of <hi>Boüillon,</hi> was taken dangerously ill of the Sickness that he died of: His Tears were the more moving and Natural, because he endeavoured to hide them. When he spoke of himself, it was with a great deal of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty and Sincerity; for Discoursing with one of his Friends, two or three Days after the Duke of <hi>Boüillon</hi> died, these were his Words; <hi>It is generally believed that I understand something of War; but there is nothing more true than that I could learn very much of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and, for Business what Talents had he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond me, and how much did he excel me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was not always happy in the choice of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:48812:51"/>his Friends, and yet he has bewailed the Death of some of them; and he had so much good Nature and Gentleness, that all the Blood he had seen spilt could never har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him, nor hinder him from being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways mindful of advancing Persons, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the Ingratitude he had met with for so many Years together. When Fortune has not been favourable too, and he has really been Unhappy; yet Fame has still done Justice to his Courage and Wisdom; and he has often gained more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, than those that had the better of him, and were more Fortunate. He was very Ambitious, but the Conjuncture of the Times, and his own Prudence, made him always moderate, and conceal it: But if he had lived in those former Ages that were so favourable to Conquerors, as his Glory had no bounds, so its probable his Fortune would not. In the time of the Regence, in the Year 1649, when <hi>Paris</hi> took up Arms against <hi>Mazarine,</hi> Monsieur <hi>Turenne</hi> enter'd into that Party, whether inclined to it by the fatal Constellation that then Reigned, or by a particular Disgust against that Minister, about his own Fortune, and that of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. He then commanded the Army in <hi>Germany,</hi> consisting of 12 or 15000 Men, almost all Strangers. He was extreamly Beloved, and Respected by them, which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48812:52"/>was not occasioned by his Merit alone, but by his being so Disinterest, and his frank and easy manner of living with the Army: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides most of the Officers owed their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to him, and had no Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Court, but by his means; so that at last, at a great Entertainment that he made them at <hi>Tubinge,</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> the principal Officers that were privately gained before, imparted the state of Affairs to the others, and so ingaged them that before they parted, they all took a solemn Oath to follow him, whereever he would lead them, and acknowledge no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Superior but himself. This Engagement was made yet more solemn, and Published with the sound of a Drum and Trumpet, and approved of by the Souldiers general Acclamations. So that in any change of a Party, there never was seen a more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Content, nor more solid appearance of trust. He declared to the <hi>French</hi> and others, that were not willing to embrace his Party, That he gave them free leave to retire, which, yet very few did. The next Day they Marched to enter into <hi>France;</hi> but the third Days March, Monsieur <hi>Turenne</hi> stopping at <hi>Spire,</hi> to finish the Bridge for the Army to pass the River upon, <hi>Longpré</hi> Lieutenant Colonel of the Foot Regiment of <hi>Vaubecourt,</hi> came in all haste to tell him, That <hi>Thoubal,</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:48812:52"/>and <hi>Chust,</hi> 2 General Officers of the <hi>Germans,</hi> who owed every thing to Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> and on whom he reposed all manner of Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, had made all the Army change their mind, and they were already marching ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. Besides, <hi>Heruard</hi> was come to <hi>Brisac,</hi> from the King, with great Sums of Mony; both for Payment of the Army, and Gratifications that were necessary to be made on such a pressing occasion. This turn was so great, and so sudden, that the same Troops that a few Days before had shewed so much Zeal for Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> had undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seized him Prisoner, if he had not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately made his escape. This was the first time that he experimented how little Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men have, both of their Life and Fortune, when that Security is only founded upon an Usurped, and Illegal Power.</p>
               <p>But it being impossible that so extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an Action could be without some conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Consequence, the following Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> was at the Head of the K. of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Army, and fought the Battle of <hi>Rethel,</hi> and lost it. And, when he saw himself out of Hopes of doing any thing else but save his own Person, he turned aside, and left those that fled, mounted upon a wounded Horse, and no body with him, but <hi>la Barge,</hi> Lieutenant of his Guard, whose Horse was hurt too. After they had marched a little
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48812:53"/>way, they saw 5 Horse coming up to them full speed; says <hi>la Barge</hi> to him, <hi>I have but one Pistol left that I can fire, and you have fired yours; What will you do, Sir? Die,</hi> la Barge, says he, <hi>rather than be carried into</hi> France, <hi>to be made a Spectacle upon a Scaffold;</hi> by that time 2 Horse-men, that were a little before the others, came to them. <hi>La Barge</hi> rid up to one and killed him with his Pistol; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther closing up to Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> laid hold on his Belt, and cried, <hi>I'll give you fair Quarter, Mons.</hi> Turenne; but he, at the same time, with his Sword run him through, and killed him, saying these Words; <hi>Traytor, I am not</hi> Turenne. One of the three Cavaliers that remained, who seemed to be an Officer, fired his Pistol at him, but missed him: After which all 3 went away, without doing any thing else, whether discouraged by the Death of their Comerades, or that the destiny of <hi>France</hi> wou'd reserve this Prince, for the great Services that he afterwards performed. In effect Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> had been lost without all remedy, both his Horse and <hi>la Barge</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wounded, and not able to go any further, but at that instant <hi>Lavaux,</hi> a Horse Officer of the Regiment of <hi>Beauvais,</hi> came to him, and gave him his Horse, to make his escape. After these 2 Actions, which he never remembred without testifying his Grief and Repentance for 'em, Posterity will not without Admiration
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48812:53"/>find him the year following, at the Head of one of the Kings Armies; and that they had an intire Confidence in him. But if this great and sudden Change be without parallel, I leave it to History to shew particularly, in all the following Actions of his Life, how Worthy of the Trust reposed in him, he shewed himself by his great Services and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Fidelity. He began to make amends for the Misfortunes he fell into the 2 former years, by 2 Actions that he performed within 12 or 15 Days; one at <hi>Gergeau,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Bleneau;</hi> and because I was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly present at them, and because both times he saved the State and the King's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, I will relate them. As soon as Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> received his necessary Orders for the Command of the Army, he left <hi>Blois,</hi> where the Court then was, and went towards <hi>Sully</hi> and <hi>Gien,</hi> to draw the Forces together that he was to command. The King was yet too young to go to the War, or take cognisance of any Business; and the Q. Mother intirely left the whole Government of the Kingdom to Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi> A few Days after Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi>'s departure, the King left <hi>Blois</hi> to go to <hi>Orleans;</hi> but <hi>Orleans</hi> shutting the Gates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, they resolved to go to <hi>Gien;</hi> and, at the same time, as they without any cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion passed under the Walls of <hi>Gergeau,</hi> a little Town upon the River <hi>Loire,</hi> the Baron
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48812:54"/>
                  <hi>de Syron,</hi> who Commanded the Army of the confederate Princes, attack'd the Bridge of <hi>Gergeau,</hi> to force his Passage, and surprize the Court. He was already Master of the Gate on the other side the River, and was making a Lodgment, or Intrenchment about the middle of the Bridge, to break down the other Gate. Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready advanced to meet the King, but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Noise of their Firing, left his Way, and threw himself into <hi>Gergeau;</hi> there he found some Foot, but so ill provided with Ammunition, that most of the Souldiers had not so much as a Charge of Powder left; whereupon, considering the strait that things were reduced to, he caused the Gates to be opened, and the Draw-bridge to be let down: And, purposely that the Enemies might hear him, he gave the Word of Command as loud as he could speak, to the Souldiers that lined the Curtain, <hi>That no one should dare to fire upon pain of Death;</hi> then making those that were with him quit their Horses; and putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self at the Head of them, he charg'd the Enemies so smartly, only with their Swords in their Hands, that he drove them from the Lodgment they made upon the Bridge; and in spight of all the Resistance they could make, though assisted by their Cannon that killed and hurt 8 or 10 Persons near him, he push<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them beyond the Bridge, and then caused
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48812:54"/>2 Arches of it to be broken down, to put the Court in a perfect state of Security. The King arriving at <hi>Gien,</hi> Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> went from thence to post himself at <hi>Briare,</hi> with what Troops he had got together, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Marshal <hi>d'Hoquincourt,</hi> who was coming to join him with a considerable body of Men, near <hi>Bleneau,</hi> he went to view his Camp and consult with him. Marshal <hi>d'Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quincourt</hi> was very brave, and bold enough to attempt and hazard all things; but he was one that accounted not foresight and precaution as necessary Military Virtues. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they had seen some of his Quarters, Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> told him several times, <hi>That he found he lay very open, and much exposed, and that he counselled him to draw nearer together, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie himself on that side next</hi> Briare. But he still answered, <hi>That there was no need to fear, and that a good Guard would remedy that Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience:</hi> But Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> was no sooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Briare,</hi> but the Marshal was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd. As soon as he heard of it he gave the Court notice of it, and march'd straight up to him with those Troops that were with him at <hi>Briare;</hi> and the Neighbourhood sent Orders to those that were farther off to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance immediately, and marched with all his Artillery within half a League of <hi>Briare;</hi> but he then learned, by those that sled, That Mons. <hi>d'Hoquincourt</hi> was Totally routed.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48812:55"/>This News was presently after confirmed by a Prisoner, <hi>Who assured him that the Enemies were making up to him, and that he had seen them upon their march.</hi> All the General Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers were of Opinion, That they should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and get near the King's Person as the only refuge in this case of Extremity. Their Forces being so unequal, but Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> whose mind was Labouring proportionably to the Importance and Danger of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, scarce answered them, but gave out his Orders to march on, and still pressed the Troops to make more haste. Whereupon <hi>la Barge</hi> came to him, and informed him, <hi>That every body murmured, and thought he went the way to lose all, if he did not return to the King;</hi> But, answered Mons. <hi>Turenne, That indeed is a fine Expedient; after the Example that</hi> Orleans <hi>has given, even before ever we received any check, Where now do you think they'll open their Gates, and admit us, when we shall come as Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives, and Beaten? No, no,</hi> la Barge, <hi>I now am weary of my Destiny; this is worse than</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel; <hi>I'll perish, or save all.</hi> The Day before, as he came back from Mons. <hi>d'Hoquincourt</hi>'s Quarters, he took notice of a Marsh that made a long defile, or narrow pass; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of this Marsh then coming into his mind, he judged by the Situation of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and as the Country lay, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to come to him, would be forced to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48812:55"/>pass that way; upon this thought, without any more deliberation, he march'd on, and so very luckily, that he no sooner had reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Marsh on one side, but the Enemy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at the other; he then had not above 3500 Men, yet with them he made Head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Victorious Army, of 14000 Men Commanded by the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They were already very much alarmed at the Defeat of Marshal <hi>d'Hoquincourt,</hi> but upon Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi>'s march they were in an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Consternation; Not doubting in the least, but that the same Misfortune would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal him; in this extremity the only refuge they had, was to get the <hi>Loire</hi> between the Enemies and the King. The greatest part of the Equipage was already sent over, and they were beginning to Unfurnish the Queens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment; and there were Pioneers ready to break the Arches of the Bridge, when the News came of this Success of Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> and they were quite reassured when they saw him, after the Enemies had retired to their Quarters, return and post himself with his Army at <hi>Briare.</hi> The same Day Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> wrote to him for his Advice, about a relation of this matter, <hi>That he intended to dispatch to</hi> Paris, <hi>and into the Provinces to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any false and disadvantagious Reports.</hi> This Narrative began with the Transactions of the Day before, and mentioned the Counsel that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48812:56"/>Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> gave Marshal <hi>d'Hoquincourt,</hi> to Fortify himself; but Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> made that Passage be omitted, saying, <hi>The Marshal was Unfortunate enough, without adding any disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Circumstance to his Misfortune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all business he used but few Words, and was an utter Enemy to long Discourses and unprofitable Circumstances; and as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, his earnest thinking made him often un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares ask Questions, which were not at all to the Purpose, and speak Words that had no Coherence. Very often he would take a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, which he could not easily overcome, and usually he was rather disgusted at the mien and air of People, than the Persons themselves; for Example, let a Man be never so brave in the Field, he could not endure him, if he took more care than ordinary against the injuries of the Weather. As for those that he had no value for, or absolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised, of what Quality so ever they were, it was with all the pain in the World that he brought himself to speak to them, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve common Measures of Civility: And the certain means to deserve his Disesteem, was to boast, and to be too much g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en to praise themselves. He could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to be counted a suspicious Man, and apt to be prepossessed, whether it were to hide those Defects, or else that his Sentiments were very opposite; and sometimes it has
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48812:56"/>hapned that he has told Secrets, that he ought to have concealed, and has appeared an open undisguised Person, even at the cost and damage of his most particular Friends. He was so much troubled to think that the World was persuaded he was easily inclined to Partiality, that though he was always ready to prefer his Friends to all the advantages that depended upon him, and to serve them with his Fortune; yet he could not speak in their Favour, with that boldness and earnestness that he could for others, who were indifferent to him, only moved to it by a Spirit of Justice and Equity, and the Zeal he had for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Glory of the King: Nay, he has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done good Offices, and procured Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments for those that did not affect him, and some there are who rejoiced at his death, who perhaps, though they knew it not, own'd the good posts they have in the World to his Endeavours and Goodness. He always lov'd his Family, but in the beginning he esteemed it less than his own Fortune, and afterwards neglected even that for his Reputation and Glory: Yet upon all occasions he assisted his Relations beyond his Ability; and in favour of some of them stripped himself of some part of his Paternal Estate, being more concerned for their wants than his own. He never va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued himself upon his giving, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits in this kind that he conferred, was with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48812:57"/>that wonderful Modesty, that is so seldom met with, and yet is so very needful to Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify and Reform that Ostentation which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most always accompanies Liberality; and this Virtue which is none of those that usually are found in old Age, was so Natural to him, that in the last years of his Life, he scattered his Money about even with more frankness than ever he had done before. In short, though he served a Noble and Liberal Master, and lived in an Age so abounding in making great Fortunes, yet he died much Poorer than he was left by his Father: And indeed one of the Qualities that he was most renouned for, was the little esteem that he had for Wealth, which he valued so little, that they say, <hi>He was Ignorant of the difference and value of the several Species of Coins.</hi> All his Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals became as Wealthy as Princes; but he who was but a younger Brother, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence had not an Estate proportionable to his Quality, threw it away without any value for it, usually saying, <hi>He would have no other Purse but the King's.</hi> However he had so numerous an Equipage, that Madam <hi>de Turenne</hi> has often said, <hi>Were it not for the King's Money, both Mons.</hi> Turennes <hi>Estate and mine would not be able to maintain us three years, at the rate that we live.</hi> One Day some of his Friends talking with him about Riches, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king some Comparisons, and Rallying him
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48812:57"/>about that Subject, <hi>He told them that, in truth, he could not comprehend the pleasure Men took in keeping their Coffers stuffed with Money; and that for his part, if at the years end he had any considerable Sums of Money left, he believed it would nauseate him as much, as, if coming from a great Feast, he should be forced to sit down to another.</hi> When he died, though he were one of the Kings greatest Favourites, and had a very considerable Government, and great Priviledges, and Commanded the Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, with almost Sovereign Authority; yet there was found but 500 Crowns in ready Money by him, with many Debts which he had contracted for the maintainance of his Troops, which the King paid immediately after his death. When he was in the County of <hi>Mark</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> Count <hi>Conismark</hi> Marshal <hi>de Camp,</hi> proposed to him a way how in 15 Days time he might gain by the means of Contributions 100000 Crowns, and that it might be done without the Courts having any Cognisance of it; but he answered him laughing, <hi>That he was obliged to him, but that after he had had many of those Opportunities heretofore, without making advantage of them, he was not minded to begin, and change his custom at this Age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the care that he took of his Person, was only to be cleanly; all other things depended upon those that served him; looking for no great Care, neither in what concerned the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:48812:58"/>service of Himself and Family; so that both at the Court and the Army one might very often come into his Bed-Chamber, without ever finding any Domestick to adress one's self to first; and for his Family Business, he always took the account in general, and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never descended to particulars. He expressed himself with no fluency of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, but rather with difficulty, which ever encreased as his Head was more upon Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. The tone of his Voice was loud, clear and firm; but when he spoke any thing that was never so little a Secret, he never thought he could speak low enough; and the general Opinion of his natural mistrustfulness was so well grounded, that his mind was seldom eased by any Secret that he imparted. He was indefatigable both of Body and Mind, and for 40 years together his Health was unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, unless by a Fever of 8 or 10 Days, and some light touches of the Gout, a little before his death. In Affairs of consequence, whether more or less difficult, he always acted with equal Vigilance, never Presuming nor Despairing of Success, and ever readier to make use of Superfluous than omit neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary Precautions. All his projects and stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems of War, were upon great Wisdom and extraordinary Foresight: But when by Chance, or the necessity of Affairs he was to commit himself to Hazard and Fortune, he
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48812:58"/>then abandoned himself to it, with all the Gayety and Boldness that even youth was capable of. Those that served under him, never knew his Designs, but the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they were to be put in Execution. He was the fittest Man in the World to ruine an Enemies Army, though his Forces were much Inferior, and end a Campagne with advantage, whose beginning afforded cause of apprehension. He never spared himself in any fatigues, but favoured others as much as it was possible. He was bold in his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prises, fearless in Danger, always even and steady in all great Actions of War and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but timorous at Court, and very unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in common Affairs. From the very moment that he was in the Army, one might distinguish a visible change in his Air and Temper, he charmed and pleased every body by his gay and easy way of living; he never shut himself up, nor retired for Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; his Gates were always open, and there was not the least mark of ostentation, or haughtiness in his Words or Actions. But when he was by Peace reduced to a privater Life, the suspension of Glory which he gained in the Wars, left sometimes room in his mind for Vanity, In this state he did look more nearly how People carried themselves to him, and somewhat change his way of living.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the Power of being a Favourite
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48812:59"/>made some Impression upon his mind and desires; but then retained either by Glory, or for fear of the Consequences, he always preferred his Liberty before any thing that might advance his Fortune. In the most dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult times he had no particular intimacy, or allyance with those that were in Power; so that he still upheld himself, and ever spoke with all the liberty and boldness of a Man of Honour, whenever he thought it absolutely necessary, either for his own Reputation, or the Service of his Master. After he had won the Battle of the <hi>Downs</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and took <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> passionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desired to make the Glory of those two great Actions his own; he would have had Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> have writ him a Letter, which should import, <hi>That in effect they were due to the Cardinal alone, and that he had projected all things in his Cabinet, and that his orders only were exactly Executed.</hi> Perhaps this Minister never shew'd a more earnest desire than in this thing. He committed the management of this business to the Count <hi>de Moret,</hi> a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of great Worth, his Favourite, and an intimate Friend of Mons. <hi>Turenne.</hi> The Court was then at <hi>Calais,</hi> and Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> at <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> The Count <hi>de Moret</hi> went to him 2 or 3 times upon other pretences, but indeed only for this matter, and used all his endeavours to put out of the Cardinals Mind
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48812:59"/>a thing that was so little agreeable to his State and Profession; and, at the same time, omitted nothing that might incline Mons. <hi>Turenne</hi> to that Complaisance that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired; but finding that he advanced not, he at last thought himself obliged to tell Mons. <hi>Turenne, That upon the first difficulties and scruples that he made, he had all the reason in the World to fear the Consequence would be very disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to his Fortune, since the Cardinal enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them with extraordinary Impatience and Vexation.</hi> Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> who was not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Hopes and Promises, was no more capable of Fear; and therefore he still an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, as he did at first, <hi>That Cardinal</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine <hi>might put into History all that was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of flattering his Ambition most, and make Posterity believe he was a great General; but as for his part he would never authorise a thing so contrary to his own Honour, and to the Truth.</hi> At the same time almost, the King fell so dangerously ill, that they gave him over for dead. The Cardinal not believing himself well with Monsieur the Kings Brother, had a mind to make sure of them that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, but he had reason to believe they would not be very favourable to him. In this extremity he had recourse to Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> and his design was to go to him, in case he were constrained to quit the Court. He therefore sent the Count <hi>de Moret</hi> to engage
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:48812:60"/>him, to offer himself to him, and oblige him to assure him the Army.</p>
               <p>The Count <hi>de Moret</hi> had order to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate this Affair, with all address imaginable, and only insinuate things instead of saying them. But as he knew that was not the way to deal with Mons. <hi>Turenne,</hi> he spoke to him of it, as he used to do, plainly without any management, or cunning; and the Vis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count promised that he would act publickly, as the Cardinals Friend; and if Monsieur came to the Crown, he would represent the state of things to him, as they then stood, and that it would be very dangerous to take them out of the Hands of a Minister, so knowing, and so well established as he was. Mons. <hi>Moret</hi> judging that the Cardinal would not be satisfied with this answer, represented to Monsieur <hi>Turenne</hi> all that he thought was able to incline him to what was desired; among other things, <hi>He told him that there is no fear but that the Queen Mother would uphold the Cardinals Fortune, and that no body could doubt the influence she had over Monsieur, nor that her protection would be wanting to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal; so that Mons.</hi> Turenne <hi>offering himself to be of this Ministers party, he might advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously, without hazarding any thing, do what was very meritorious, and what he would never forget.</hi> The Viscount answered, <hi>That in all probability things would go after this manner,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:48812:60"/>but that he would never promise any more than he had done; adding, that no advantage how great soever it were, should ever tempt him either to make those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, that he might hereafter break, or be reduced to the necessity he had been formerly.</hi> The Cardinal was so little contented with this Answer, that after he had several times sworn the ruine of M. <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne,</hi> he spoke many extravagant things, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Fury, and other times mov'd by Fear and Despair. But the King recovering, and the War continuing; the Cardinal either suspended, or forgot his resentment. He was pleased with the Company of Learned and Ingenious Men, but he had no kindness for those that were profest Wits; they never tasted of his Bounty, nor had he much share, or mention in their Productions. When he had no Business, he lov'd to divert himself, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at his Meals, but without any excess. He was soon mov'd to laugh at pleasant Discourse; and he himself Rally'd very handsomly, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with abundance of Discretion and Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. He was pleased with any Ingenious Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and lov'd to read good Books, especially History, and made his use of it; but seldom was heard to Quote it. He was not able to bear Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, as such, but when it was disguised under the appearance of Friendship, that any one took an easy Natural way to praise him. He easily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded matter of Discourse; and it was not very difficult for a Flatterer to insinuate himself into his Confidence and Belief, and make his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of it.</p>
               <p>He was born a Protestant, and professed that Keligion above 50 years, without being well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in it; at that Age he began to doubt,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:48812:61"/>but without making it known to any one, and then he endeavoured to inform by reading, which only serv'd to multiply scruples; at last he was forced to come to Conferences, but only by way of Conversation, for fear of letting his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be known. The Q. Mother discovered it, and spoke to him of it, letting him know, that besides the consideration of saving his Soul, there were some Temporal advantages that moved her so earnestly to desire his being a Catholick. This Discourse, tho able to make a great Impression upon many other Persons, stopp'd all these good motions, and caused him to remain some years as he was, neglecting to inform himself any farther. For it is most true, that he feared lest his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version should be followed by some extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Favour, capable of making the Honesty, and Sincerity of his intentions be ill interpreted, and of blemishing his Honor: But, at last, pressed by his Conscience, he opened his Mind; first to the B. of <hi>Condom,</hi> who is now B. of <hi>Meaux;</hi> then to the B. of <hi>Tournay,</hi> who was his particular Friend, and spoke also to his Nephew the Card. <hi>de Boüillon,</hi> whom it seems God had a mind to employ to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish this great Mans Conversion. At length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that he was out of the true Church, he abjured before the A. B. of <hi>Paris,</hi> without giving any notice of it till the preceding Evening, nor did the K. himself know of his design but a little before.</p>
               <p>The Love and Veneration that the Army al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had for him, was very much encreased in his last Campaigns, which appeared among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Demonstrations of it the year before his Death, in that wonderful expedition when he march'd to attack the Enemies in <hi>Germany.</hi> One Day when the Army
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:48812:61"/>was passing through a long defile, or narrow pass, he turned a little aside out of the way, and lay down behind a Bush; while he slept, there the Souldiers saw him, and finding him almost covered with snow, they run in all haste into the neighbouring Fields, to cut down Boughs of Trees to make him a Hut; and as they were making it, there came by some Troopers who seeing the Hut did not cover him from the Weather, and keep him dry, they strove who should first lay their Cloaks over it, to make a kind of Tent: With the Noise that they made he awaked, and asking them, <hi>Why they did not March, and what they were doing? We are preserving our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> said they, <hi>that is our chiefest Business, for if we lose him, we shall never see our Country more.</hi> Whereupon, he not being able to make 'em leave off their Work, and not willing to shew his Absolute Power, by any rigorous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or Usage upon this occasion, he was forced to get on Horse-back again, and March too. All his Campaigns since the War against <hi>Holland,</hi> being such prodigies of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Judgment, which would afford matter for several Volumes, if any one would justly describe them. But after having escaped several dangerous Engagements, he was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Field; being hit on the Breast by a random Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-shot. The News of his Death wonderfully affected the Gentry and Nobility, and made a great impression upon all sorts of People, who for many Days, could speak of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this great loss. Many there were that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, who had never seen him; some moved to it by the remembrance of his Actions, others when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered the Services he might have done for the future; and all were generally touched with Grief at the relation of his Death. At <hi>Paris,</hi> and in the neighbouring Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but particularly in the Frontiers of the Country, where the seat of War was, their Grief was much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, because they knew him better, and were used to see him every Winter. To conclude; his loss look'd like to the total defeat of some Army, where every particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the Kingdom had lost either his Estate, or his dearest Friend. Though in his life time there was published a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison between him and <hi>Caesar;</hi> I believe, that I may observe, that if the likeness did not hold, by reason of the different ways to Glory, under the Government of a Monarchy, and that of a Common-wealth, so there was as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48812:62"/>in the manner of their Deaths. Caesar <hi>was murther'd in time of Peace by his fellow Citizens, whom he had opprest; but</hi> M. Turenne, <hi>belov'd and esteem'd by every body, lost his use with his Arms in his Hands, serving his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, without any other interest or motive, but that of his Duty and Reputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He began to appear under <hi>Lewis</hi> 13. being upheld by his own Deserts and Quality; only he liv'd without any Favour, or Disgrace, all the time that Card. <hi>Richelieu</hi> Govern'd. Under Card. <hi>Mazarines</hi> Ministry, he had several turns of Fortune, but she was always prosperous, and favourable to him the last 20 years of his life. He had a 1000 occasions of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reputations and Glory, which all the Histories of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> will immortalize. He esteem'd himself the happier in that he serv'd a K: that had all the Qualities to be desired in a Master, and who treated him with so much intimacy and esteem, that he lov'd him as his Friend. I leave to those that write his History, to relate to how high a point of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he carried the reputation of the Kings Arms in his last War, and what his Projects and Wishes were, concerning the Affairs of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the great advantages that he promised himself when his Death hapned. I will now only add, that he was ever so far from Presumption, that when ever he began to hope well of any enterprise, his hopes might be accounted on as a certainty of a happy Success.</p>
               <p>The King did him the Honor to cause him to be buried at St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> with the Crown'd Heads of <hi>France;</hi> (an Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or which was never granted but to him, and the Constable <hi>Bertrand du Gueselein</hi>) which occasion'd this Epitaph.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Turenne <hi>à son Tombeau parmi ceux de nos Rois,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>C'est le fruit glorieux de ses fameux Exploits;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>La</hi> France <hi>veut par là couronner sa Vaillance,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A fin de faire voir aux Siécles à venir,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qu'elle fait peu de difference</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>De porter la Couronne ou de la soûtenir.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Turenne</hi> interr'd among our Princes lies,</l>
                     <l>The just reward for all his Victories;</l>
                     <l>'Tis the last debt <hi>France</hi> to her Hero owes,</l>
                     <l>And gratefully lets after Ages know,</l>
                     <l>How small a difference ought to be shown,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt him that wears, and that supports a Crown.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48812:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>